<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The reason why not infant sprinkling but believers baptism ought to be approved is because the Lord Jesus Christ, his forerunner, and apostles preach't it, and practic'd it as hereby will further appear by Scripture authority in about fourty texts, with notes on every text : to which is added, how infant sprinkling came in fashion, the evil tendencies of infant sprinkling, answers to objections, differences betw. believ. baptism and inf. sprink. with several other things / by a believer baptiz'd.</title>
            <author>Doe, Charles.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1694</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 144 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36265</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D1827B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33458</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13356218</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13356218</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99244</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36265)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99244)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1548:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The reason why not infant sprinkling but believers baptism ought to be approved is because the Lord Jesus Christ, his forerunner, and apostles preach't it, and practic'd it as hereby will further appear by Scripture authority in about fourty texts, with notes on every text : to which is added, how infant sprinkling came in fashion, the evil tendencies of infant sprinkling, answers to objections, differences betw. believ. baptism and inf. sprink. with several other things / by a believer baptiz'd.</title>
                  <author>Doe, Charles.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>83 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed:</pubPlace>
                  <date>1694.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Charles Doe.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Infant baptism --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Baptism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99244:1"/>
            <p>THE Reaſon Why <hi>Not Infant Sprinkling,</hi> BUT BELIEVERS BAPTISM, Ought to be approved, Is becauſe the Lord Jeſus Chriſt his Fore-runner, and Apoſtles preach't it, and practic'd it; As hereby will further appear <hi>By Scripture Authority</hi> In about Fourty TEXTS, With Notes on every TEXT.</p>
            <p>To which is added,</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>How Infant Sprinkling came in Faſhion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>The Evil Tendencies of Infant Sprinkling.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anſwers to Objections.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Differences betw.</hi> Believ. Baptiſm <hi>and</hi> Inf. Sprink. With ſeveral other things.</p>
            <p>By a Believer Baptiz'd.</p>
            <q>
               <p>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Mark 16.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>The</hi> Eunuch <hi>ſaid to</hi> Philip, I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God.— And they went down both into the Water, both <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and <hi>Philip</hi> baptized him,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Act. 8.36, 37, 38.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed 1694.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:99244:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:99244:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Friend,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF you are ſincerely inquiſitive about the Worſhip of God, and deſire the <hi>Reaſons Why</hi> Believers Baptiſm ought to be approved, and Infant Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling rejected; then be pleaſed to conſider this ſmall Treatiſe, which as my <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding I commend to you, and that in ſincerity and love to our Lord Jeſus Christ his Goſpel, and your Information.</p>
            <p>Wherein you may obſerve that the method taken to diſcover right Baptiſm by, is the cleareſt from de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that could be; becauſe every Text about Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, is taken in order, as Recorded in <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> that thereby it may fairly and clearly appear to you as well as to me, That 'tis <hi>indeed Believers baptiſm that is the Goſpel Ordinance requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and that it is not Infant Sprinkling: Beſides, if you, as I have been, are rightly in love with your own Salvation, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, then you will find an aptneſs in your Soul to be obedient to the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt, as parts of the Will of God. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Apoſtles ſaying, <hi>We are his Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſhip created in Chriſt Jeſus to good Works, Eph. 2.10.</hi> and all from a principle of Love to God Chriſt, his Goſpel and goodneſs, and the delight of them begotten in the Soul of the Regenerate.</p>
            <p>This Soul conſidering redeeming Love, deſires it may glorify God, according to <hi>John 15, 8. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is my Father glorifyed, that ye bear much fruit, ſo ſhall ye be my Diſciples. John 14.21. He that hath my Commandments, and keepeth them, he it is that loveth me:</hi> And again; <hi>If ye keep my Commandments, ye ſhall abide in my Love, even as I have
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99244:3"/>kept my Fathers Commandments and abide in his Love, John 15.10.</hi> And therefore it is that many in our Age that have an effectual work of Grace upon their Souls, <hi>have had alſo ſome Workings about Obedience to this great Goſpel Ordinance of Believers Baptiſm:</hi> Tho' ſome of them (by <hi>Maſter ſave thy ſelf,</hi> Mat. <hi>16.22.</hi>) have been baffled off, and their Light put out, and thoſe Motions stifled, whereby they have turned their back upon it.</p>
            <p>But the Lord preſerves this Light in ſome, and hath ſo in me; and therefore I ſubmit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to the preſcribed Rule God hath given, tho' thereby. I converſe among a poor &amp; diſpiſed People, according to the Apoſtle's obſervation of the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Saints, <hi>1</hi> Cor. <hi>1.26.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To follow a Religion, becauſe it is in Faſhion, is not my Rule.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I have four ſorts of People to deal with, and they require four ſorts of conſiderations to convince them, and therefore I give variety.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1.</hi> The Ignorant World that do not like believers baptiſm, becauſe it is commonly ſpoken evil of.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> The ſuperſtitious World that don't like it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it condemns part of their ſplendid way of worſhip</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> The Profeſſor that diſſents from that ignorance and ſuperſtition, and zealouſly purſues a Reform'd, yet a political way.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> The Converted that admires the Love that work'd about the Salvation of the Sinner, and yet is ſomewhat blind about baptiſm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But thoſe among whom I expect the Doctrine of believers baptiſm ſhould be effectual, are all thoſe that the Crucified Riſen Jeſus<hi>'s Lo I am with you,</hi> ſhall give it ſucceſs to.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:99244:3"/>
            <p> The Sinner that's fallen in Love with the Lord Jeſus, taketh him at his Word, and in that hear of first Love, dare do any thing for God, <hi>Luke 7.47.</hi> This Soul is juſt touched with a Coal of holy Fire from the Altar, and is all in a flame, and takes the Glory of the World for Stubble. And as by Revelation from the Father, <hi>Mat. 11, 27. Mat. 1.17.</hi> It Believes that the mighty Jeſus is the Son of God, ſo it Believes that this Sovereign Will ought to be obeyed. And accordingly with the Fortitude that contemned <hi>Nebuchadnezzars</hi> Golden Image in the Face of a Fiery Furnaco, <hi>Dan. 3.</hi> Reſolves to be <hi>Baptized or Dipped,</hi> Saying, I muſt by baptiſm ingage in my Lords Service, to fight the good fight of Faith, and lay hold on Eternal life, thro good report and evil report, for what am I, that I ſhould pretend to a better way of obedience then my Saviour hath appointed.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Chriſtian Friend <hi>C. D.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>1693.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <postscript>
               <p>Yet for thoſe of my Chriſtian Brethren that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re reſolved upon their way of <hi>Infant Sprinkling,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in peace leave them to the Lord &amp; to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>houghts and way, and keep the <hi>Scripture Reaſon</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f <hi>Believers Baptiſm,</hi> for as many as ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave the grace to receive it. And ſo as I began <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Love to our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I deſire to end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n love with all that love our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            </postscript>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <pb facs="tcp:99244:4"/>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99244:4"/>
            <head>CHAP. I. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.1, 2, 5, 6.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> In thoſe Days came <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Wilderneſs of <hi>Judea.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> And ſaying, Repent ye, for the Kingdom of Heaven is at Hand.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> Then went out to him <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the Region round about <hi>Jordan.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">
                     <hi>6.</hi> And were baptiſed of him in <hi>Jordan,</hi> confeſſing their Sins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That as ſoon as this firſt Evangeliſt <hi>Matthew</hi> had by direction of the Spirit of God, given a Relation of the Birth and preſervation of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; he preſently tells us of <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> preaching and baptizing, thereby ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying, That Faith in Chriſt hath the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, and that Obedience and Profeſſion of Faith by baptiſm comes next in order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> The Perſons to be baptized were ſuch as confeſt their Sins; <hi>but not Infants carried thither, and ſenſeleſs of Sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in,</hi> They were baptized or dipped in a River, which they went to of their own Will, <hi>but not ſprinkled with a little Water out of a b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſon, or ſuch like brought to them, or they car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to it whether they would or no.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Repentance was firſt preached, and then upon Signs of Repentance the people were afterwards baptized.</p>
            <p>So that the Subjects of, and manner of baptiſm, <hi>neither were Infants nor Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:99244:5"/>
            <head>CHAP. II. Matth. <hi>3.7, 8.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> But when he <hi>(John)</hi> ſaw many of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees and Sadduces come to his baptiſm, he ſaid unto them, O Generation of Vipers, who hath warned you to fly from the wrath to come?</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Bring forth therefore Fruits meet for Repentance.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That thoſe Perſons that gave not Signs of Repentance were rejected from baptiſm; or thus, <hi>No Perſons were admitted to baptiſm but upon Signs of Repentance;</hi> which <hi>John</hi> ſaw was wanting in ſome perſons, and thoſe he rejected as not intended in his Commiſſion. And therefore <hi>Infants</hi> are not intended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> The Infants of believing Gentiles cannot be concerned in baptiſm, becauſe not ſo much as the Infants of the <hi>Jews</hi> or <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were; for <hi>John</hi> required Signs of <hi>Repentance,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore admittance to baptiſm, becauſe only the true believers are the New Teſtament <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites,</hi> and not Infants: <hi>They are not all Iſrael that are of Iſrael,</hi> Rom. 9.6. Rom. 2.28 29.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> If ſome will make the Infants of believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parents Church-members by baptiſm, or by Sprinkling, becauſe they reckon them in the Covenant, why will they not continue them Church-members when they are grown up? as If their growing up to Maturity, were a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the Covenant. And indeed, theſe in the Text being a generation of Vipers, ſhew that believers <hi>Children</hi> are not in the <hi>Covenant,</hi> ſo much more than others <hi>as to be baptiſed, for</hi> John <hi>hear ſets that Covenant aſide from giving right to baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:99244:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> Mat. <hi>3.9.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>And think not to ſay within your ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father: For I ſay unto you, that God is able of theſe Stones to raiſe up Children unto Abraham.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I note, That Parents being believers, do not entitle their Children to baptiſm: For God hath neither ſo confined himſelf by promiſe or the ordinary diſpenſation of his Grace, as Experience teacheth. Tho' he had promiſed many things to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed by natural Generation, yet none could by that Generation claim a peculiar priviledge in Goſpel things: For inſtance, this of baptiſm is now denyed them, they being without Repentance, an effect of another Generation. A being born again, born of God; <hi>And if ye be Chriſt's, then are ye Abraham's Seed, and Heirs according to promiſe,</hi> Gal. 3.29. <hi>And you hath he quickned, who were dead in Treſpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Sins,</hi> Eph. 2.1. And therefore let none reckon themſelves better than others, becauſe they were born of believing or profeſſing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, <hi>For we are all by Nature the Children of Wrath,</hi> as well as others, Eph. 2.3.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> If our right to this Ordinance (as ſome would have it) be founded in our believing Parents, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.4. how is it that an awakened Soul that hath been ſprinkled in its Infancy, ſees it ſelf in an utter loſt condition by nature? having no right to the Covenant of promiſe, or the ſigns of it by any natural inherent Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or birth-priviledge: And when by Faith it comes to have a view of the Lord Jeſus, then it ſees that all religious viſible priviledges are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in the way of believing in him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:99244:6"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> Mat. <hi>3.11.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>I indeed Baptize you with Water unto Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. But he that cometh after me, is mightion than I, whoſe ſhoes I am not worthy to bear; he ſhall Baptize you with the Holy Ghoſt and with Fire.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That Repentance is ſuch an eſſential qualification for Baptiſm, that God in ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering his Goſpel Church, Commiſſionates his prophet <hi>John</hi> to preach it, to prepare fit Members for that Viſible Church, and that alſo upon ſigns of Repentance, to admit them by Baptiſm. And that without thoſe Signs, Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm ſhould not be adminiſtered; whereby it appears that God hath made Repentance as the root or Tree, and Baptiſm as the Branch, and ſo Goſpel Baptiſm cannot actually have a being without ſigns of Repentance; God hath ordained that Goſpel Baptiſm, ſhould be the Fruit on the Signs of Repentance. If you rake away the cauſe, the effect ceaſes, and accordingly <hi>John</hi> Baptized none but them in whom he found the cauſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, John</hi> foreſeeing the coming of the Lord Jeſus, and conſidering the manner of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing to be over-whelming in Water, takes oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion from thence, to foretell of the abundance of the Holy Ghoſt, that the Saints ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dewed with; &amp; ſo it was fulfill'd, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.2, 3, 4. <hi>And ſuddenly there came a ſound from Heaven, as of a ruſhing mighty wind, and it filled all the houſe where they were ſitting. And there appeared unto them cloven tongues like as of fire, and it ſate upon each of them. And they were all filled with the Holy Ghost,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99244:6"/>
            <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> Then cometh Ieſus from <hi>Galilee</hi> to <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> unto <hi>John,</hi> to be Baptized of him.</p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14.</hi> But <hi>John</hi> forbad him, ſaying, I have need to be Baptiſed of thee, and comeſt thou to me?</p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15</hi> And Ieſus anſwering, ſaid unto him, ſuffer it to be ſo now, for thus it becometh us to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill all Righteouſneſs; then he ſuffered him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That baptiſm is of divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the ſon of God himſelf ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to it as to Righteouſneſs, that he might fulfill all the will of God; notwithſtanding, that the Prophet <hi>Iohn</hi> the Adminſtrator, thought that the dignity and innocency of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Chriſt was above that Adminiſtration: yet Jeſus ſaw his duty, as man ſtanding in the room of the ſinner, to give for him a perfect Obedience to divine Juſtice, and therefore ſubmitted to <hi>Baptiſm</hi> or <hi>Dipping,</hi> leaving an Example for our imitation, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> It was firſt Jeſus<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s choice to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and not <hi>Iohn</hi> the Adminiſtrators to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize him; and ſo in the choice, Jeſus was Active and <hi>Iohn</hi> Paſſive: but Infants are altogether paſſive, and not at all active for ſprinkling, but rather by crying, ſhew their diſlike.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Jeſus to fulfill his Fathers righteous Will of baptizing, came where was much water, tho it was many miles to it; but if a few drops would have done, then that might have been had where he was, and <hi>Iohn</hi> might have come to him.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99244:7"/>
            <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.16, 17.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> And Jeſus when he was baptized, went up ſtraitway out of the Water, and lo the Heavens were opened unto him, and he ſaw the ſpirit of God deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending like a Dove, and lighting upon him.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17.</hi> And lo a voice from heaven, ſaying, This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That the Lord Jeſus in his baptiſm, had not water brought to him, neither did he withdraw to a Rivolet nor ſtand by the River-ſide, nor did a little water ſuffice, nor did he it in private; but he went down ſo far, and deep into the River, that the Text is expreſs, <hi>When he was baptized, he went up straight way out of the water.</hi> Mark, he went up out of the water, is the curious penning of the matter by the Holy Ghoſt, to ſhew the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable depth our Lord went into the water to be dipt, that it may appear much water is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the right Adminiſtration of baptiſm. This was his ſolemn Entrance into his pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Miniſtry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> God the Father, the Creator of all things, the high and lofty one that inhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth Eternity, gives his Teſtimony to this his own ordinance of baptiſm, or dipping, by the Holy Ghoſt's glorious and miraculous appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Heaven in a viſible deſcent, and the Father approving his Son's ſubmiting to his righteous Will.</p>
            <p>Never was any Church-Ordinance uſher'd in with more Glory than the Ordinance of believers baptiſm.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99244:7"/>
            <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Mat.</hi> 21.25, 26, 27.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="25">
                     <hi>25.</hi> The Baptiſm of <hi>John,</hi> whence was it, from Heaven or of Men? And they reaſoned among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſaying, if we ſhall ſay from Heaven, he will ſay unto us, why did ye not then believe him?</p>
                  <p n="26">
                     <hi>26.</hi> But if we ſhall ſay of Men, We fear the People, for all hold <hi>John</hi> a Prophet.</p>
                  <p n="27">
                     <hi>27.</hi> And they anſwered Jeſus, and ſaid, we cannot tell.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That ſome Men <hi>(tho in the days of Chriſt)</hi> diſowned the Doctrine of <hi>baptiſm up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Repentance,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> the firſt Preacher and Adminiſtrator of it: Becauſe there was, as they thought, a peculiar ſaving Priviledge, unalterably annexed to the Children of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> tho when grown up were impenitent. Joh. 8.33. but it was but a pharaſaical thought.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Many that are not in love with Chriſt diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover it, by not being in love with his Ordinance, for his ſake:</hi> And ſome again are willing their own Invention may ſerve for his Ordinance.</p>
            <p>And it appears, <hi>John</hi> 2.23. that this <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> of <hi>John</hi> was in much Water, and therefore he abode and preached in a place near much Water; but if a little Water would have done, then he might have Travel'd, and Preached and Sprinkled in the Hill Countrey, all over the Land; but to baptize or Dip, he muſt be where is much Water, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore abode at <hi>Enon,</hi> a place by the River <hi>Iordan,</hi> becauſe there was much Water there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Behold our Jeſus indiſputation ſheweth, that Dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after repentance is from heaven, but Sprinkling before ſigns of Repentance is of Man's invention.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:99244:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:99244:8"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:99244:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. VIII. <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.19.20.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="19">
                     <hi>19.</hi> Go ye therefore, and teach all Nations, bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiking them in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20.</hi> Teaching them to obſerve all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I have commanded you, and lo, I am with you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways, even unto the end of the World. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That here is the Commiſſion of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm, given by our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, King of Saints, and Law-giver to his Church: And that the Miniſters of his Goſpel are to preach firſt, &amp; upon the ſucceſs of their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, baptize only thoſe who believe the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Therefore unleſs Infants hear the Word preached, and become thereby convinc't of ſin, and the excellency of a Saviour, they are not within the reach of the commiſſion for baptiſm; but that Infants do not do: and therefore they that ſprinkle or baptize before preaching, ſet up their own folly againſt the wiſdom of God, by doing the laſt firſt, juſt contrary to the <hi>Commiſſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, to baptize either Infants or Men, or Women before they believe, is to make all ſeem Church and no World, or rather continue all World and make no viſible Church: but our Saviour will have a Church out of the World. And therefore he ſaith to his Church, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.19. <hi>I have choſen you out of the world, therefore the world hates you;</hi> and accordingly believers are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to be baptized, to diſtinguiſh them from the World. (<hi>See more pag.</hi> 15.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> This promiſe of Chriſt's preſence with his people, is upon condition of obſerving the method of baptizing after preaching, for preſerving his viſible Church from mixing with Unbelievers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:99244:9"/>
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.4, 5.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> John did baptize in the wilderneſs, and preach the Baptiſm of Repentance for the remiſſion of ſins.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> And there went out to him all the land of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea, and they of Jeruſalem, and were all baptized of him in the River of Iordan, confeſſing their ſins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, that this Evangeliſt alſo relates that <hi>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> was <hi>adminiſtred</hi> not at a <hi>river</hi> but in a <hi>riv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, by dipping of perſons that went out, not carried out, and upon confeſſion of ſins, which Infants cannot do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Tho the Phariſees that thought they knew the Law did not receive Baptiſm, yet God found a people that did upon confeſſion of ſins; and therefore let not us that are ſincere for Chriſt and his Goſpel, be afraid of the reproach of ſome Eccleſiaſtical Perſons, but value the love of God, for the text ſaith, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall be aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of me and of my words in this adulitrous and ſinful Generation, &amp;c. Mark</hi> 8.38. <hi>Matth.</hi> 10.32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> I wonder how the Infant Sprinkling Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters dare ſay, <hi>In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt, I baptize thee, &amp;c.</hi> When they do but Rantize or Sprinkle, and not Baptize or Dip.</p>
            <p>If they will ſprinkle in ſome bodies name and not in their own, it is then (to my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing) more proper and ſafe for them to ſay, <hi>In the Name of the Fathers. Popes, and religious Men, I ſpri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kle thee</hi> (according to the declared Will of the <hi>Milevetan</hi> Council in this caſe, <hi>It is our Will that, &amp;c.</hi> and of the 5th. Council of <hi>Carthage, An.</hi> 416. <hi>We will that,</hi> &amp;c. (but this is not God's Will) and then they'l put no fallacy upon God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of baptiſm, nor ſpeak untruth in the name of the Trinity.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99244:10"/>
            <p> And let me here ſpeak directly to ſome Chriſtians that are for Infant Sprinkling; what tho you believe perſonal Election, is there therefore a neceſſity that you muſt ſprinkle your Infants, believing that that election runs only in your Line by natural Generation? Tho it may be you can ſay as a great many can, That truly I do not know whether there be another chriſtian of my Generation or no; for they all by their Lives diſcover Ignorance and Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief of the Lord Ieſus, or at moſt make but a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odiccan</hi> profeſſion: and then my brethren, what incouragement have you to reckon that Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on will run to your Generation after you, and that your Infants ſhould be ſprinkled.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Moreover,</hi> perſonal election is a ſecret reſiding only in God; then how can you perſonally ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Election before their perſonal believing?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Furthermore,</hi> election gives no right to baptiſm until the elect perſon be taught or called, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the commiſſion of preaching &amp; baptizing.</p>
            <p>God's order of working about the ſalvation of a ſinner, is, God elects and his Miniſters calls; and the ſpirit going with the Word regenerates, and upon that comes a bending to obedience and profeſſion. <hi>Or thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>God elects, and Man preaches, and then God regenerates, and Man baptiſeth. <hi>God works firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Is the decree of ſalvation. <hi>2dly.</hi> The pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it. <hi>3dly.</hi> The change made in the ſoul. <hi>4thly.</hi> The ſign thereof, and a profeſſion which by the will of God ought to be done by dipping, (<hi>ſee p.</hi> 27.) as a lively Emblem of cleanſing in the merits of Chriſt, the River of Water of Life.</p>
            <p>As God in order of time, hath placed Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on before Sanctification, ſo he hath placed teaching before baptizing.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="10" type="chapter">
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:99244:10"/>
            <head>CHAP. X. <hi>Mark</hi> 1.9, 10, 11.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="9">
                     <hi>9.</hi> And it came to paſs in thoſe days, that Jeſus came from Nazareth of Galilee, and was baptized of John in Jordan.</p>
                  <p n="10">
                     <hi>10.</hi> And ſtraight way coming up out of the Water, he ſaw the Heavens opened, and the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit like a Dove deſcending upon him.</p>
                  <p n="11">
                     <hi>11.</hi> And there came a Voice from Heaven ſaying, thou art my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That the Evangeliſt <hi>Mark</hi> as well as <hi>Matthew,</hi> is imployed by the Holy Spirit of God, to let us know, That our Lord Jeſus Chriſt at Man's Eſtate, ſubmitted to <hi>dipping,</hi> notwithſtanding the Dignity of his Perſon, <hi>being God manifest in the Fleſh, Immanuel, God with us:</hi> behold, this mighty perſon bears a Teſtimony too, and puts a glory upon baptizing or dipping of viſible Saints, by being himſelf baptized in the River <hi>Jordan</hi> at Thirty years of Age, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>If God hath appointed Dipping, why ſhould Man pretend to ſprinkle? as if Man was wiſer than his Maker, or had a Soveraignty over God's Worſhip; I think none but Papiſts claims that Prerogative, tho others practice it.</p>
            <p>But ſenſible Chriſtian, do thou chooſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Dipping, and reject Infant Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. For the Lord Jeſus choſe to be ſo bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and He hath dignity and ſoveraignty to command thy Obedience, and this ſort of Obedience, even <hi>believers baptiſm</hi> in much water.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="11" type="chapter">
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:99244:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. XI. <hi>Mark</hi> 11.30.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="30">
                     <hi>30.</hi> The Baptiſm of Iohn, was it from Heaven or of Men? Anſwer me.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That alſo the Evangeliſt <hi>Mark</hi> mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth that our Saviour himſelf put the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion for us, that profeſs believers baptiſm, <hi>Was it from Heaven or of Men?</hi> This Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion being cloſe to the point, puſled the great Men of that Day that oppoſed <hi>Dipping,</hi> ſo that they ſeemed to ſtand as it were ſpeech<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, therefore our Saviour cloſes upon them again, ſaying, <hi>Anſwer me:</hi> Anſwer the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And then they ſet their carnal Reaſon to work to find out ſome ſophiſtical Anſwer, and preſerve their Reputation among the People; and the Learnedſt Anſwer that they could find, was a ſubtil one, <hi>We cannot tell.</hi> See their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy in the Text: <hi>And they reaſoned with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> (not with the Scriptures) <hi>if we ſhall ſay from Heaven, he will ſay, Why then did ye not believe him? If we ſhall ſay of Men, they fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the People,</hi> (would be in a rage for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to Divinity, and yet deny Dipping a Heavenly Inſtitution) <hi>for all men counted that John was a Prophet indeed, and they anſwer'd and ſaid unto Jeſus, We cannot tell, &amp;c.</hi> Mark 11.31, 32, 33. And thus our Lord Jeſus ſhews That Dipping after ſigns of Repentance, is an undeniable Doctrine.</p>
            <p>God will accept nothing in his Worſhip but what he hath appointed, and that's ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to conſtrain me to ſubmit to the great Goſpel Ordinance of believers baptiſm, tho many <hi>cannot tell.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="12" type="chapter">
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:99244:11"/>
            <head>CHAP. XII. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.15, 16.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15.</hi> And he ſaid unto them, go ye unto all the World, and preach the Goſpel to every Creature.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved, but he that believeth not, ſhall be damned.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That this Promiſe, <hi>he that believeth &amp; is baptiſed, ſhall be ſaved,</hi> ſeems to carry a great force in being baptiſed, as well as in <hi>Believing.</hi> But unqueſtionably it carries, that believing is eſſential to ſaving, and it is to go before bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tizing, and not baptizing before believing; for that is juſt contrary to the Text, Man's Will for God's, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>John</hi> 4.23.</p>
            <p>Believing and baptizing you ſee are joyned in the Text, and therefore what God hath joyned together, let no man put aſunder.</p>
            <p>And were it indeed that Infants were dipp'd, which is the right Mode of baptizing, it would not further their ſalvation, they not <hi>belit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</hi> God having reſerv'd the way of their ſalvation as a ſecret peculiar to himſelf, even by <hi>the unſearchable Riches of Chriſt:</hi> Then <hi>how can Infants have any thing to do with Baptiſm;</hi> for Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm here in the Commiſſion is not annexed to a natural birth, but to Preaching &amp; believing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> To ſecure dipping from ſuppoſed danger, <hi>all the World</hi> in the Text ſignifieth <hi>cold</hi> Countries as well as hot, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe <hi>Lo, I am with you,</hi> preſerves, <hi>yea I never heard of</hi> any believer that had hurt in <hi>Baptizing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Here's a Commiſſion for believers bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm; but where is any Commiſſion for Infant Sprinkling? And they that act in the Kings Name without's Commiſſion, are invaders of the Kings prerogative Royal, and inſtead of obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they ſet themſelves in the <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="13" type="chapter">
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:99244:12"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIII. Luke 3.2, 3.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> —The word of God came unto John, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> And he came into all the Country about <hi>Jordan,</hi> preaching the baptiſm of Repentance, for the remiſſion of Sins.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> alſo bears a Teſtimony to <hi>believers baptiſm</hi> upon ſigns of repentance, and not to Infants, nor ſprinkling, for they can give no ſigns, nor can a <hi>little water</hi> ſerve; for in the text it was done in a River.</p>
            <p>Conſider God's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anger with <hi>Iſrael,</hi> for (among other things) changing his <hi>Altar of Earth,</hi> Stone, or chittim wood, into an <hi>Altar of Brick,</hi> Iſa. 65.2, 3. but Infant ſprinklers ſay, Why is not Sprinkling as good as Dipping, ſeeing it will as well repreſent the thing ſignifyed by Baptiſm? But that's their miſtake, and God can tell beſt, Why not? and 'tis beſt for us to obey and Dip, when God ſaith <hi>Dip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> thought, that God's choice and order was too preciſe, and that therefore another place was better, as now of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant ſprinkling, ſome think tis better than be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers baptiſm. Said Naaman, <hi>Are not Abana and Pharpar Rivers of Damaſcus, better than all the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rael: May I no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> waſh in them, and be clean: So he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rned and went away in a rage,</hi> but <hi>his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> adviſed him to obey, 2 Kings 5.12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>No repenting, no baptizi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g.</hi> If the Queſtion be put, <hi>Tho is to be baptized?</hi> Why the anſwer is, <hi>He that repenteth. For the Goſpel is to be preached only to ſuch as are capable of believing and repenting, and conſequently of being baptiſed there upon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, Iohn</hi> preached in all the Country near the River, becauſe of much water.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="14" type="chapter">
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:99244:12"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIV. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.7, 8.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7.</hi> Then ſaid he to the Multitude that came forth to be baptized of him, O generations of Vipers who hath warned you to fly from the wrath to come.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> Bring forth therefore Fruits worthy of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and begin not to ſay within your ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father; for I <hi>(John)</hi> ſay unto you, that God is able of theſe stones to raiſe up Children unto Abraham.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I Note, That being the natural Children of believing Parents, tho grown perſons, doth not intitle them to this holy Ordinance; for God is able by his Spirit in the Call of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, to raiſe up Children unto <hi>Abraham;</hi> and as he was counted the Father of the Faithful, ſo his Children of the promiſe muſt be believers; for of the Race of the Gentiles (as we in <hi>England</hi> are) we cannot be the ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> but as we are believers and faithful; and ſo <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi> becomes our Father, and then comes in our claim to the promiſe to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to his Children: And accordingly hear <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> rejects natural generation, and calls for <hi>regeneration Fruit, &amp;c.</hi> for 'tis not <hi>Abraham</hi> to our Father, but believing that gives right to <hi>baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, every days experience teacheth us, that tho multitudes of Infants are ſprinkled, yet but few, very few of them, when at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity, ſhew ſigns of Faith and Repentance.</p>
            <p>And on the other hand, experience every day teacheth us, that very many of them that have Repentance, or an effectual work of grace up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their ſouls, are thoſe that cannot plead the priviledge of having believing Parents; then
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:99244:13"/>pray what peculiar right to baptiſm hath the children of believing Parents more than others?</p>
            <p>Beſides, if the now believer that was ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in his Infancy, have ſwaying reaſons to believe, that neither of his Parents were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers (and ſuch there are;) then by what rule did his Parents ſprinkle, or as he calls it baptize him? And by Vertue of what promiſe doth the believer reckon his Infant Baptiſm effectual or valid to him, ſeeing his Parents were Unbelievers? For the promiſe was made as he reckoneth, only to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of believing Parents. Pray then doth not the unbelief of his Parents make his baptiſm void for want of a ground to found his baptiſm on? Yes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Abraham</hi> was not Father of our Engliſh Nation: <hi>And therefore think not to ſay within your ſelves, we have Abraham to our Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As we came to Chriſt (not by the Will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of the will of God) ſo cometh more, be their Parents believers or unbelievers. <hi>Or thus,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our children cannot be the children of <hi>Abraham</hi> till they believe as he did.</p>
            <p>Again, formerly as well as now, a generation of <hi>Vipers</hi> too often comes of believing Parents, then how are they in the covenant more than others.</p>
            <p>As 'tis not election but ſanctification, that actually qualifies men for heaven, ſo 'tis not E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection but Believing, that actually qualifies for baptiſm. The Elect are choſen to be ſanctified as well as to be ſaved, and accordingly are called by the Goſpel to believe, and then be baptiſed, and that as a ſign of their Faith; and all this is before they are actually ſaved.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="15" type="chapter">
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:99244:13"/>
            <head>CHAP. XV. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.12, 13.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Then came alſo Publicans to <hi>(John to)</hi> be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, and ſaid to him Maſter what ſhall we do?</p>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> And he ſaid unto them, exact no more than that which is appointed you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I note, That the Publicans according to the ſaying of Jeſus, are apter to receive the Goſpel, than ſome Profeſſors are.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Publicans and Harlots go into the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God before you,</hi> Mat. 21.31. <hi>And the Publicans Juſtified God, being baptiſed with the Baptiſm of Iohn,</hi> Luke 7.29.</p>
            <p>A ſubmitting to the Call of the Goſpel, and diligence to learn the Duties of it, are ſigns of Faith and Repentance, and qualifies perſons for Baptiſm, <hi>What ſhall we do? What ſhall I do,</hi> Acts. 16.30. is always the queſtion of the Repenting, Believing Sinner, that is fallen in Love with Jeſus, (under the ſenſe of the need of ſaving from his ſins,) And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that Jeſus hath ſomething for him to do, he is willing to ſhew that Love, by doing ſomthing commanded by Jeſus, even to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, <hi>(If any thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s to be done by the Creature, then Infants are excluded.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Thus we read of many ſorts of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Phariſees, Sadduces, all the People, yea Jeſus himſelf, but yet not a Word of Infants, the point in hand.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> John <hi>doth not mind whether they were the ſeed of believing Parents or no, but requires Repentance as a ſign of faith, to qualify for baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="16" type="chapter">
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:99244:14"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVI. <hi>Luke</hi> 3.21, 22, 23.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="21">
                     <hi>21.</hi> Now when all the People were baptiſed, it came to paſs, that Ieſus alſo being baptiſed, and praying, the Heaven was opened.</p>
                  <p n="22">
                     <hi>22</hi> And the Holy Ghost deſcended in a bodily ſhape, like a Dove, upon him, and a voice came from Heaven, which ſaid, Thou art my beloved Son, in thee I am well pleaſed.</p>
                  <p n="23">
                     <hi>23.</hi> And Jeſus himſelf began to be about thirty years of Age, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I note, That three Evangeliſts, witneſſeth that baptiſm was adminiſtred on people, by dipping them in a River, and not on Infants by pouring or ſprinkling a little water on them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Tho Jeſus was Circumciſed in his Infancy, yet to be baptiſed he muſt be at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity. Tarry till he be juſt entering upon his Religious publick work, tho he be about thirty years of Age firſt.</p>
            <p>The Father hath given his teſtimony to <hi>dipping</hi> at maturity, by inſtituting it, and beholding his Sons obedience, &amp; by a voice from Heaven, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>This is my beloved Son in whom I am well pleaſed</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Son hath given his Teſtimony to it, by owning it his Fathers will, and practiſing it, and giving his Apoſtles Commiſſion for it.</p>
            <p>The Holy Ghoſt hath given his Teſtimony to it, by deſcending in a bodily ſhape at its Adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Let Infant Sprinklers ſhow ſuch Testimonies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then what glory in the parts of Worſhip is there that exceeds this glory of the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of theſe three Infinite Perſons, in the one eternal Being?</p>
         </div>
         <div n="17" type="chapter">
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:99244:14"/>
            <head>CHAP. XVII. <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29, 30.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="29">
                     <hi>29.</hi> And all the people that heard him, and the Publicans juſtified God, being baptized with the Baptiſm of <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="30">
                     <hi>30.</hi> But the Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves, being not baptized of him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> The great difference between two ſorts of People, the common people, and the ſuperſtitious. The common people, the poor imbrace the Doctrine of the Goſpel, tho the worldly wiſe and ſuperſtitious reject it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Publicans justified God,</hi> that is, the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectors of the Taxes, which the Jews paid the <hi>Romans,</hi> who were infamous for their Exactions, were convinced of their Sins by <hi>Johns</hi> Miniſtry, and acknowledged the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Goodneſs, and Mercy of God. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing baptized with the Baptiſm of John,</hi> they believed his Baptiſm was from Heaven, and ſubmitted unto it as a divine Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, confeſſing their Sins.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But the Phariſees and Lawyers,</hi> the Rabbies of the Age, <hi>rejected the Counſel of God againſt themſelves,</hi> continued impenitent, <hi>not bringing forth Fruits meet for Repentance;</hi> and refuſed ſubmiſſion to the wiſdom of God in his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious diſpenſation, being not baptized of <hi>John.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> It is the indiſpenſable Duty of Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to be baptized, becauſe 'tis not only in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, but there's not any Text that leaveth them to the liberty of leaving it undone.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="18" type="chapter">
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:99244:15"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Luke <hi>20.4.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q> The Baptiſm of John, was it from heaven or of men?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> That alſo the Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> minds, that our Lord Jeſus defended <hi>John</hi>'s Baptiſm as a Doctrin, by divine Authority.</p>
            <p>And that <hi>Baptizing</hi> is <hi>Dipping,</hi> is alſo manifeſt by the literal, proper, and natural ſignification of the Greek word <hi>Baptizo,</hi> which all our <hi>Lexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> and Learned Men, yea Criticks in the Tongues, with one conſent, do ſay, That <hi>Baptize</hi> is <hi>Dip,</hi> yea, ſuch a Dipping as is uſed in <hi>Bucks,</hi> where Cloaths are waſh'd, to waſh the whole body, to dip over head and ears. The Engliſh and French keep the Greek word <hi>Baptiſm</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tranſlated (which I reckon either a fault in the Tranſlators, or a way left whereby the peoples ignorance about <hi>Baptiſm</hi> was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.) But the <hi>Dutch</hi> tranſlate plainly in their own Language, <hi>Doopen</hi> to Dip.</p>
            <p>And that the word <hi>Baptizo</hi> doth ſignify to <hi>dip</hi> or <hi>plunge</hi> under water. Conſider theſe Scriptures for the preſent, Mat. 3.16. John 3.22, 23 Acts 8.38. Rom. 6.4. And theſe Authors follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Stephanus, Scapula, Budaeus, Caſaubon, Zan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius, Spanhemius, Taylor</hi> and <hi>Hammond.</hi> For which conſult <hi>Legh</hi>'s <hi>Critica Sacra, Taylor</hi>'s <hi>Ductor Dubicantium,</hi> and <hi>Hammonds Annotat.</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the New Teſtament.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> To baptize before Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>entance, is juſt contrary to <hi>John</hi>'s Practice; for he bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized no Infants, and rejected perſons that gave no ſigns of Repentance, Mat. 3.7, 8.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="19" type="chapter">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:99244:15"/>
            <head>CHAP. XIX. <hi>John 1.</hi> 28.31.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="28">
                     <hi>28.</hi> — <hi>Jordan,</hi> where <hi>John</hi> was baptizing.</p>
                  <p n="31">
                     <hi>31.</hi> — That he <hi>(Jeſus)</hi> ſhould be made manifeſt to <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Therefore am I come baptizing with Water.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That this fourth Evangeliſt <hi>John,</hi> alſo beareth Record to the firſt Inſtitution of belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers baptiſm which <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt adminiſtred in the River <hi>Jordan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, John's</hi> baptiſm was by Divine Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority; he called people by his Miniſtery to Faith in Chriſt, and expected good Works as the fruit of that Faith: And here began to be laid the Foundation of the New Teſtament Church gathered out of the World, by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel call of Faith, Repentance, and baptiſm; theſe People he divides, he gathers the good and throws the bad away; admits the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting, the coming Sinner, and Rejects the reſt; not an Infant baptized, nor a grown perſon Sprinkled in this Heavenly baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Old Teſtament</hi> Church was National, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of the Natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants bought with Money and Proſelyter, who were circumciſed, to diſtinguiſh them from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, by expreſs command from God: but the New Teſtament Church is congregation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al, conſiſting of a ſeparate People, gathered by the call of the Goſ el out of the World, and are reputed the Spiritual Seed of <hi>Abr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ham,</hi> by believing as he did, <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> 3.6, 7. <hi>Even as</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, <hi>believed God, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted to him for Righteouſneſs. Know ye there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re, that they which are of Faith, the ſame are the children of</hi> Abraham.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="20" type="chapter">
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:99244:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. XX. <hi>John</hi> 3.22, 23.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="22">
                     <hi>22.</hi> After theſe things came Jeſus and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples into the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> and there he tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with them, and baptiz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d.</p>
                  <p n="23">
                     <hi>23.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> alſo was baptizing in <hi>Enon</hi> near to <hi>Salim,</hi> becauſe there was much Water there.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> That our Lord and Saviour own<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Johns Baptiſm,</hi> by practiſing the ſame, and as <hi>Iohn</hi> his Fore-runner had prepared the way, by preaching Repentance and Baptiſm, but not an Infant concerned therein.</p>
            <p>So <hi>Christ</hi> admitted none to his <hi>baptiſm,</hi> but ſuch as made an <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctual profeſſion of faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Tho the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſon why Jeſus and his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and <hi>Iohn</hi> alſo baptized in <hi>Enon,</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was much <hi>Water</hi> there, a fit place for <hi>baptizing;</hi> yet ſome men nowadays by their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, reckon themſelves wiſer than <hi>Iohn,</hi> or the <hi>Diſciples</hi> and <hi>Ieſus</hi> alſo; and they chooſe a place where is a little <hi>Water,</hi> a ſpoonful ſerves their turn, <hi>and this is juſt contrary to the Text</hi> of being a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Enon, becauſe there was much water there.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, <hi>Infant Sprinkling</hi> is contrary t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Baptiſm</hi> in all the parts of it.</p>
            <p>Surely, 'tis clear, that this Text proves, there is ſomething in much Water ('tis material to Baptiſmal Obedience) and that a little is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> handful is not ſo proper as a River fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>If by plauſible pretences one Error be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted into the Church, then all Errors may follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="21" type="chapter">
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:99244:16"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXI. <hi>John</hi> 4.1, 2.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> When therefore the Lord knew how the Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees had heard that Jeſus made, and Baptized mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Diſciples than <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Tho Jeſus himſelf baptiſed not, but his Diſciples.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I note, That the baptiſed were <hi>Diſciples,</hi> Chriſt's Schollars, before that he baptiſed them. And tho he baptiſed more Diſciples than <hi>John,</hi> yet he baptiſed no Infants, for the Text faith, <hi>they were Diſciples,</hi> perſons that had learn'd ſome of Chriſts Doctrines.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Baptiſed more <hi>Diſciples,</hi> proves, that Infant Sprinkling is only a Humane Invention, a Counterfeit deviſed, to politically make all that are born in a Nation Church-members, or viſible Chriſtians before they have Faith or Repentance, of which ſort the Antichriſtian Church is full. Which ſecures their Prieſtly Grandeur, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet thoſe whom Chriſt and his Diſciples baptiſed, were not Infants but Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, beſides Sprinkle they did none.</p>
            <p>Moreover, If <hi>Infant Sprinkling,</hi> had been an appointment or Ordinance of <hi>Jeſus Christ,</hi> there would have been ſome Command or Example in Scripture to warrant the ſame. But where the Scripture hath no Tongue to ſpeak, we ſhould have no Ear to hear, that we be not guilty of <hi>Will-worſhip.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſhould any conclude that ſome of theſe baptiſed Diſciples were Parents, yet, we find no mention of the Baptiſm of their little Children, for the Lord Jeſus knew that they had no right to Baptiſm tho their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents were believers.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="22" type="chapter">
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:99244:17"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXII. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.28, 39, 41.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="28">
                     <hi>28</hi> Then Peter ſaid unto them, Repent and be baptiſed every one of you in the name of Jeſus Chriſt, for the rem ſſion of ſins, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
                  <p n="39">
                     <hi>39</hi> For the Promiſe is unto you, and to your Children, and to all that are afar off, even a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</p>
                  <p n="41">
                     <hi>41</hi> Then th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y that gladly received the Word, were Baptiſed, and the ſame day were added to them about Three Thouſand Souls.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That upon the <hi>Jews</hi> being by <hi>Peters</hi> Preaching convicted of ſin, and crying out, <hi>What ſhall we do,</hi> ver. 27. <hi>Peter</hi> anſwers, and commands Baptiſm even as he Commands Repentance, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent &amp; be baptiſed,</hi> &amp; the Reaſon given why they ſhould now repent and be baptiſed, is becauſe <hi>now they are according to promiſe, called by the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel to believe, Repent and be baptiſed;</hi> but not called to be <hi>Sprinkled firſt,</hi> and repent afterwards.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> When People repent before they are baptiſed, they are then in the way or order, that the Wiſdom of God hath aſſigned; but <hi>Baptizing</hi> or <hi>Sprinkling</hi> before <hi>believing</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting,</hi> contradicts the order appointed by God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> This Duty, <hi>Repent and be baptiſ d,</hi> is not only injoyned them, but after Generations, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.32. — <hi>the Remnant whom the Lord ſhall call.</hi> Every ones Children that ſhall be called, be called by the Goſpel in all the World; ſo full and free are the tenders of the Goſpel, for the promiſe is to many, <hi>even as many as are called,</hi> Rev. 7.9. <hi>I ſaw a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99244:17"/>which no Man could number, of all Nations,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Of all theſe that the Promiſe was made to and to their Children. <hi>None were baptized but thoſe that gladly received the Word:</hi> But it doth not appear, that any Infants did or could be capable of receiving the Word, and therefore they could not be the fit ſubjects for <hi>baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Tho three thouſand believers were added, yet there was not one believing Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent that had an Infant either baptiſed, or ſo much as ſprinkled, for they that were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, were only thoſe that gladly received the Word. For in the Text, is not a word of little ones; <hi>Baptiſm</hi> is only for thoſe that gladly receive the Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> The Primitive way of admitting Church Members, was upon a profeſſion of Faith, a Believing: Whereupon having that ſign of a <hi>Change,</hi> a Regeneration, the Miniſters then obedientially baptiſe them, as directed by Chriſt in their Commiſſion, they being by baptiſm viſibly added; But they were not ſprinkled firſt, and never believe after, as a great many are.</p>
            <p>Why ſhouldſt thou think, that the ſame God and Father that work't about thy ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation before thou though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt of thy ſelf, and hath by his grace effectually called thee, ſhould not alſo have a deſign of ſaving grace upon ſome Unbelievers Children, as well as upon thine? nay, it may be, it is upon theirs and (if any be rejected) not upon thine; for it was not for any Worthineſs in thee, that thou waſt called; and therefore, what's in thee, that thy
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:99244:18"/>Children ſhould be more than others, when others are of the ſame lump with thy ſelf? And thy Corruptions too much work up, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding grace hath been at work upon thee, that ſtill 'tis a miracle that thou art ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; Nay, thou wouldſt never be ſaved, if grace did not eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> abound, and mercies, great and manifold mercies follow thee every where, and all thy life long; ſo that 'tis by grace ye are ſaved, and the ſ me grace in the Text is free to, <hi>as many as the Lord our God ſhall call.</hi> And when called, then are they accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly proper Subjects for baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Let men make the Covenant as firm as they pleaſe, or as now a days make what alterations they will, and put who they will into it, yet that gives Infants no right to Baptiſm, until ſigns of Regeneration; for all things in God's Worſhip muſt have a Warrant from God's Word, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1.2. <hi>chap.</hi> 9.24, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.12. And baptiſm is always in Scripture annexed to ſigns of Regeneration.</p>
            <p>He that doth not blind himſelf, may ſee by experience, that neither the Children of Believers nor Unbelievers give ſigns of being in the Covenant, until they are grown to Years of underſtanding, and the moſt never do it at all; how then according to your own reckoning ſhould they have right to baptiſm? And tho you ſprinkle them upon a ſuppoſition, that they are in the Covenant, yet you will not admit them to the Lords Table upon that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, until they ſhew ſigns of Regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, then why ſprinkle them? Is their grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng to be Men, a growing out of their Priviledg? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut indeed they were never in that.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="23" type="chapter">
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:99244:18"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP. XXIII.</hi> Acts <hi>8.12.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q> But when they <hi>(of Samaria)</hi> believing Philip's Preaching the things concerning the Kingdom of God, and the Name of Jeſus Christ, they were Baptized both Men and Women.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That believing in Jeſus Chriſt, hath a Spiritual tendency to obedience &amp; Believers baptiſm, <hi>tho in our degenerated Age, many Converts motions thereto are ſtifled by ſeeming Truths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> How expreſs the Text is, <hi>both Men and Women were baptized;</hi> but yet not a word of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants,</hi> for they indeed were never baptized nor intended for it; becauſe they were incapable of believing, or anſwering the Call of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>When the <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women believed,</hi> they then were baptiſed, and this is compleatly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Commiſſion of teaching and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16. And indeed baptiſm in the beſt kind could not be an Ordinance of God, but by vertue of his Royal Commiſſion.</p>
            <p>I have read that a Learned Doctor of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith thus. <hi>I have ſeen what my Learned and worthy Friend,</hi> Dr. H. <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>and others ſays in defence of Infants Baptiſm, and muſt confeſs, I do not a little wonder, that Men of ſo great Parts, ſhould ſay ſo much to ſo little purpoſe, for I have not ſeen any thing like an Argument for it,</hi> Dr. Bar. to Mr. T.</p>
            <p>Believing and Baptiſm are joyned together, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>He that believeth and is baptiſed ſhall be ſaved.</hi> What God hath jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red together let no Man put aſunder, for th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e is no diſſolving the Native Un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, tho diſunion of living together, hath been ſuffered becauſe hardneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rt, <hi>Matt.</hi> 19.18.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="24" type="chapter">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:99244:19"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXIV. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37, 38, 39.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Philip <hi>by the Spirit preached to an</hi> Ethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian <hi>Eunuch as he was riding in his Chariot.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="36">
                     <hi>36.</hi> And as they went on their way, they came unto a certain Water, and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> ſaid, ſee here is Water, what doth hinder me to be baptized?</p>
                  <p n="37">
                     <hi>37.</hi> And <hi>Philip</hi> ſaid, if thou believeſt with all thy heart, thou mayſt; and he anſwered and ſaid, <hi>I believe that Jeſus Chriſt is the Son of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="38">
                     <hi>38.</hi> And he commended the Chariot to ſtand ſtill, and they went down both into the water, both <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch,</hi> and he baptiſed him.</p>
                  <p n="39">
                     <hi>39.</hi> And when they were come up out of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, the ſpirit of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od caught away <hi>Philip.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That <hi>they went down both into the Water, and they came up out of the Water,</hi> which plainly proves, that ſtanding by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was not enough, though much Water; then how ſhould ſtanding by a Baſon of water be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, or taking a handful be enough? but both muſt go into the Water: And the Text, to be ſure, to faſten the going down into the Water upon our minds, doubles the expreſſion, and names the perſons particularly by Name, both <hi>Philip</hi> and the <hi>Eunuch</hi> went down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Water. But why doth the Holy Ghoſt make this repetition, but to ſhew that much Water is eſſential to baptiſing, dipping muſt be eſſential to dipping, and is not a Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, Dipping and Baptizing being all one, <hi>Baptize is Greekiſh and Dip is Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At my writing on this Text, I being in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>any with one of the Diſſenting Miniſters in
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:99244:19"/>in <hi>London,</hi> that practiſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h Infant Sprinkling, I put one Queſtion to him, <hi>viz. Whether much water was not needful for the right performing of Baptiſm?</hi> And after a little <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> he ſaid, <hi>I will grant you that it was the Primitive Practice in baptizing to dip; for 'tis foolery</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>for any man to deny it;</hi> and he alſo acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the Greek word <hi>baptiſo</hi> had our Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlators put it into <hi>Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh,</hi> muſt have been dip. Tho he contradictingly ſaid, <hi>That dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping was but a Circumſtance,</hi> and might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at diſcretion be aſtered to Sprinkling, that carrying the ſame ſignification in it as dipping doth: but I anſwered, <hi>That Dipping was not a Circumſtance, but eſſential to baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>It's irrational, nay, its making a thing to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy its ſelf, to ſay, That Dipping is not eſſential to Dipping.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And who is the Man that may at his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion alter God's Ordinance? Man muſt neither add to, take from, nor change the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of Chriſt, without <hi>Infalibility.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is one of the boldeſt preſumptions Man can aſpire unto, to innovate in the Worſhip of God; nothing can be more affronting to his Sovereign Autho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ity, Wiſdom and Puri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, then for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oor creatu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es to mix their own contrivances with his moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ure Appointments, <hi>Deut.</hi> 12, 32. Ch. 18.20. <hi>Jer.</hi> 26.2. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.6. <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.1, 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> 'Tis not another but thou thy ſelf that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>elieveſt, that is to be baptized; yea, every o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> is to act for himſelf, <hi>an other mans do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing will not excuſe thee.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="25" type="chapter">
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:99244:20"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXV. <hi>Acts</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.18.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Ananias <hi>put his hands on</hi> Saul, <hi>and ſpake:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="18">
                     <hi>18.</hi> And there immediately fell from his eyes as if it had been ſcales, and he received ſight forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, and aroſe and was baptized.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> That here is a miraculous Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Saul,</hi> or <hi>Paul,</hi> by many illuſtrious circumſtances, all clos'd up as it were with a ſeal, <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> as if his Converſion would not have been complete without <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> ſo ſacred and of great import is Baptiſm to follow converſion; <hi>Baptiſm is the great demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Expreſſion of a Change in the Soul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Paul</hi> aroſe (that is as much as to ſay) went ſome whither to be baptized, where was much water; for elſe a little, if that would have done, might have been brought to him, as it is now a days to children; but to be dipt, <hi>he muſt ariſe,</hi> Joh. 14.13. Mic. 2.10. <hi>and go to ſome place where is much water.</hi> Jer. 13.4. 2 Sam. 17.22.</p>
            <p>And this we find in Scripture was the conſtant practice of the Apoſtles in obedience to their commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly this Apoſtle practiced it himſelf, and praiſeth the <hi>Corinthian</hi> Saints for their punctual obſervation of Ordinances, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.2. <hi>Now I praiſe you Brethren, that ye remember in all things, and keep the Ordinances as I deliv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ered them to you.</hi> Baptiſm was delivered in the Pattern by Dipping, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17. not by Sprinkling: and therefore Sprinkling will not ſerve, but it muſt be Dipping; <hi>they went down into the Water,</hi> Acts 8.38.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="26" type="chapter">
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:99244:20"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXVI. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.46, 47 48.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="46">
                     <hi>46.</hi> — Then anſwered <hi>Peter. 47.</hi> Can any man forbid water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we.</p>
                  <p n="48">
                     <hi>48.</hi> And he commanded them to be baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That ſigns of Converſion are all along made the <hi>Qualifications</hi> or <hi>Reaſons</hi> why perſons ſhould be baptized: But Infants giving no ſigns of Converſion, are therefore not qualified.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Water Baptiſm is ſo great a Duty, that the Apoſtle commanded it upon find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the perſons qualified; but Infant Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling being no where commanded, or directed is a clear proof, that the Children of the Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Parents of thoſe times, were not qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified for baptiſm by their Parents believing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> That which the Apoſtles did bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptize with, was that which Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to baptize with, <hi>viz.</hi> Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Perſons receiving the ſpirit of God, is not ſufficient to excuſe them from the call of the Goſpel to be baptized with water, but is rather a ſure qualification for water Baptiſm, for no man can mend the Apoſtles Commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Sprinkling is not here command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Peter,</hi> but Dipping; he commanded them to be baptized, that is dipped in the name of the Lord Jeſus. Surely if Sprinkling had been e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, the Apoſtle would not have injoyned dipping, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Baptizing in much water is made an Emblem of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of grace and glory,</hi> Rev. 1.5, 6. tho ſome people choſe a few Drops.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="27" type="chapter">
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:99244:21"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP.</hi> XXVII. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.14, 15.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14.</hi> And a certain woman named <hi>Lydia,</hi> a ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler of Purple of the City of <hi>Thyatyra,</hi> which worſhipped God, heard us, whoſe heart the Lord opened, that ſhe attended to the things which were ſpoken of <hi>Paul.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15.</hi> And when ſhe was baptized, and her houſehold, ſhe constrain'd us to abide at her houſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> That <hi>Lydia</hi> was a Merchant-woman, a ſtranger in this country where ſhe lived, and in appearance a ſingle Woman, or unmarried, becauſe there is no mention of either husband or children as is uſual, where ſuch are concerned nay, ſhe is named as principal; not by a Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands name, but by her own name <hi>Lydia,</hi> not as having an Husband nor in an Husbands buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but her own <hi>a Soller,</hi> which further clears, that ſhe had no husband nor children here where ſhe lived. Note her Speech, <hi>Not in our Houſe, but in my Houſe;</hi> ſhe properly calls it <hi>her Houſe,</hi> whereby it clearly appears, the had no husband. And why <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> my ſhould imagine ſhe had children in her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uſe is very ſtrange, and but a poor ſhift to bring in Inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling by? but that ſhe had a ſervant or two is probable, becauſe i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to her buſineſs of Trade and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut for any to affirm, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e had h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Text is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and leaing ſo much to the contrary, much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and except it be affir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſo that they were not of maturi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ve, this Text will do Infant Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>kling no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rvice. For a ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition will not be ſufficient ground to build
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:99244:21"/>a Church Ordinance upon, at leaſt when many Scriptures appear againſt it. <hi>If thou believest, thou may'ſt be baptizid,</hi> was <hi>Philips</hi> terms to tho <hi>Eunuch;</hi> and upon theſe terms <hi>Lydia</hi>'s Servants might have right to baptiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> if <hi>Lydia</hi> had a husband in her Houſal at <hi>her</hi> baptiſing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tis ſtrange that notice ſhould be taken of the Wives baptizing and not of the Husbands; nay, if ſhe had had a Hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>band there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſurely he would have been named, and if no husband, then why children?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> If <hi>Lydia</hi> had a husband, 'tis ſtrange that ſhe ſhould in deſcription be deſcribed to be a Woman and not a Wiſe, and that ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed to ſuch a city and not to ſuch a perſon, and that the Trade ſhould paſs in her name, and not in her Husbands, and that ſhe was the Houſekeeper, not a Lodger.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Had <hi>Lydia</hi> had a Husband with her, whereby a greater probability of children might ariſe, it is very likely it would have been ſaid, That <hi>Lydia</hi> and her husband, as well as <hi>Lydia</hi> and her Houſehold; or <hi>Lydia</hi> the Wife of ſuch a Man, and himſelf were baptized, and their Houſhold, <hi>Judg.</hi> 4.4. or had ſhe been a Widow, to have been called ſo as the Woman of <hi>Sarepta,</hi> to whom <hi>Elias</hi> was ſent, was called <hi>a Widdow,</hi> Luke 6.26. And again, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.12. <hi>The only Son of his Mother, and ſhe was a Widdow.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, In all the forty Texts about bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm there is not one Child mentioned, then why any ſhould imagine that <hi>Lydia</hi> had any, is ſtrange; for here is no more ſign of <hi>Lydia</hi> hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Children then there is of <hi>Pauls.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="28" type="chapter">
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:99244:22"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP.</hi> XXVIII. <hi>Acts</hi> 16.30, 31, 32, 33, 34</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Paul <hi>and</hi> Sylas <hi>being caſt into Priſon, an Earthquake comes, the chains and Doors open, and amazingly convicts the Jaylor, who came trembling to them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="30">
                     <hi>30.</hi> And brought them out, and ſaid, Sirs, What must I do to be ſaved?</p>
                  <p n="31">
                     <hi>31.</hi> And they ſaid, believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and thou ſhalt be ſaved and thy houſe.</p>
                  <p n="32">
                     <hi>32.</hi> And they ſpake unto him the Word of the Lord, and to all that were in his houſe. <hi>33.</hi> And he took them the ſame hour of the night, and waſhed their ſtripes, and was baptized he and his ſtraight way.</p>
                  <p n="34">
                     <hi>34.</hi> And when he had brought them into his houſe, he ſet meat before them, and rejoyced, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in God, with all his houſe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That the Goſpel was preached to all that were in his houſe, and he and his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived it, and rejoyced <hi>believing in God with all his houſe.</hi> And theſe that rejoyced believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, are they that were baptized.</p>
            <p>But if it be ſuppoſed, that he had <hi>Children,</hi> then 'tis as ſuppoſable he had none; and if ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that they were baptized, it can be only ſuch mature children that the Text ſaith, <hi>Rejoyced, believing with all his houſe;</hi> for the Text notes that ſuch, and none other were baptized. And therefore, theſe could not be Infants.</p>
            <p>A houſe of people converted together, good News! <hi>They all believed, and were all baptized;</hi> yea otherwiſe the Jaylors believing could not ſave his houſe, nor one perſon, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. Neither will one man's believing ſerve another to be baptized by, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.37.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="29" type="chapter">
            <pb n="41" facs="tcp:99244:22"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXIX. <hi>Acts</hi> 18.8.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="8">8. And <hi>Criſpus</hi> the chief Ruler of the Synagogue believed on the Lord with all his houſe; And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> hearing, believed, and were baptized.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That here again is the believing of a whole houſe, and their baptizing upon it; and ſo alſo as many of the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that believe were baptized, and no more.</p>
            <p>And why is there ſuch care taken all along by the Holy Ghoſt, to tell us of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, when we are told of baptizing, but to ſhew, That there was no baptizing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the parties firſt believing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Believing and baptizing,</hi> baptizing upon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving is the fix'd order of the Goſpel, and is about Fourty times mentioned, but through out the Teſtament, not a word of Infant Sprinkling.</p>
            <p>And therefore it appears, that the Holy Ghoſt hath given us ample proof of what is indeed the Ordinance of baptiſm, having ſo often told us, Repetition upon Repetition.</p>
            <p>And then, how dare any man reckon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf wiſer than the Holy Ghoſt, by making alterations, and ſaying, A little water is as good as a great deal, and Sprinkling is as good as Dipping, and that Infants that do not believe may be baptized as well as believing Men and Women. <hi>Faith comes by hearing. Rom.</hi> 10.17. And therefore Infants muſt be without Faith, or do not believe.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="30" type="chapter">
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:99244:23"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXX, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.3, 4, 5.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Paul <hi>diſcourſing the Brethren at</hi> Epheſus.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> And he ſaid unto them, unto what then were you baptized? and they ſaid unto <hi>John's</hi> baptiſm.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Thou ſaid <hi>Paul, John</hi> verily baptized with the baptiſm of Repentance, ſaying unto the People, that they ſhould believe on him that ſhould come after him, that is, on Chriſt Jeſus.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> When they heard this, they were baptized in the name of the Lord Jeſus.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That <hi>John's</hi> baptiſm and Chriſt's were the ſame, only that <hi>John's</hi> was upon profeſſion of Faith in Chriſt to come, and Chriſt's baptiſm is upon profeſſion of Faith in him already come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> To baptiſe a perſon by Dipping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Profeſſion of Faith, that was Sprinkled in Infancy, is no Rebaptiza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Do you ſay Infa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Sprinkling is lawfull, becauſe the Scripture doth not forbid it? Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> I ſay it is unlawful becauſe the Scripture doth not appoint it, for what is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> commanded is forbiden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Samu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l</hi> ſaid, <hi>hath the Lord as great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in burnt Offerings and Sacrifices as in obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the voice of the Lord; behold, to obey is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>to then Sacrifices,</hi> &amp;c. 1 Sam. 15.22, 23.</p>
            <p>And theſe Believers are they that according to Gods order and his peoples, anſwer to the Goſpel call ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht to be baptiſed, to manifeſt that they do indeed ſeperate form the World and ſhow forth Chriſts death and Reſurrection.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="31" type="chapter">
            <pb n="43" facs="tcp:99244:23"/>
            <head>
               <hi>CHAP.</hi> XXXI <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Paul <hi>relates how he was converted; and that then</hi> Ananias <hi>ſaid to him;</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16,</hi> And now why tarriest thou? ariſe, and be baptized, and waſh away thy Sins, calling on the name of the Lord,</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That baptiſm is not to be delay'd when a perſon is converted, but to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtered, as the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> knew beſt how to appoint the manner, that it ſhould be a proper ſign, and to a true believer a real token of the certainty of his being waſhed and clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the blood of Chriſt. O the unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able boundleſneſs and depth of the Riches of Chriſt, repreſented by much water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All things under the Law were cleanſed by blood; without ſhedding of blond was no remmiſſion;</hi> and this is the <hi>River of water of Life that Saints are waſhed in,</hi> of which the Ordinance of believers Water <hi>baptiſm,</hi> is a lively <hi>Emblem, A River of Water of Life, the boundleſs Ocean of the Merits of Christ's blood.</hi> Rev. 1.5. <hi>Him that loved <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s and waſhed us from our ſins in his own blood.</hi> And ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.6. according to <hi>Zech.</hi> 13.1. <hi>In that day there ſhall be a Fountain opened to the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe of</hi> David, <hi>and to the Inhabitants of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>for ſin and for uncleaneſs</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> To waſh away filth, Sprinkling is not ſo proper as dipping, but here ſins are to be waſht away by baptiſm, ſaith an Apoſtle.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="32" type="chapter">
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:99244:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXII <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.3, 4, 5.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="3">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Know ye not that ſo many of us as were baptized into Christ, wer b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ptized into his Death.</p>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> Therefore we were buried with him by baptiſm into death, that as Chriſt was raiſed from the dead by the glory of the Father, even ſo we alſo ſhould walk in newneſs of life.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <hi>5.</hi> For if we have been planted together in the likeneſs of his Death, we ſhall be alſo in the like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Reſurrection.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I Note,</hi> That Faith in the Death of Chriſt is needful to baptiſm; baptiſm, or in Engliſh Dipping, was a ſign of the death and burial of Chriſt, and ſo the riſing up out of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a ſign of the riſing of Chriſt out of his Grave, which clearly ſhews that <hi>not ſprinkling</hi> but <hi>dipping</hi> is proper to ſignify Death, burial, and Reſurrection, and not only that of Chriſt's but of our death to ſin, &amp; reſurrection to newneſs of life in an holy walking before God and Men, as ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> after his <hi>converſion</hi> and baptiſm; the <hi>life that I now live is by Faith in the ſon of God;</hi> and let the time paſt ſuffice for your vain converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and that we ſhould by Faith ſee that as our bodies are buried in the water, <hi>ſo our ſins are bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with Chriſt in the Grave; and as our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies are raiſed out of water, ſo by Faith ſee Chriſt riſen for our Justification,</hi> and that we that are baptized, are no more <hi>strangers and foreigners but viſibly fellow Cittizens with the Saints.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> By us that were baptized, the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle meaneth believers, not Infants; for ever ſince his converſion, he numbereth himſelf with believers, Saints by calling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="33" type="chapter">
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:99244:24"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXIII. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13, 14, 15, 16, 17.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> — Were ye Baptized in the Name of <hi>Paul?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="14">
                     <hi>14.</hi> I thank God that I baptiſed none of you but <hi>Criſput</hi> and <hi>Gains.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">
                     <hi>15</hi> Leaſt any ſhould ſay, that I baptized in my own name.</p>
                  <p n="16">
                     <hi>16.</hi> And I baptized alſo the houſhould of <hi>Stephan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> beſides, I know not that I baptized any other.</p>
                  <p n="17">
                     <hi>17.</hi> For Chriſt ſent me not to baptize, but to preach the Goſpel, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That <hi>Paul</hi> doth not mean Chriſt did not at all require him t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> baptize, or that it was not in his Commiſſion; but he means, he was not chiefly ſent to do it; theſe Scriptures, are ſo to be underſtood, <hi>John</hi> 6.27. 1 <hi>Tim</hi> 2 14. <hi>Epheſ</hi> 6.12. for, if he had no command from Chriſt at all to baptize, then he did evil in baptiſing <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius, &amp;c. — Act.</hi> 16.32.33. But it is evident, that <hi>Paul</hi> declared the whole counſel of God, &amp; was cammand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Chriſt to baptiſe, becauſe he did baptiſe thoſe in Chriſts Name, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.13, 15.</p>
            <p>And again, the only reaſon <hi>Paul</hi> gives for his not baptiſing, is, <hi>least any ſhould ſay, that I baptized in my own name,</hi> and ſo ſet up for a party to my ſelf, and divide Chriſt's Church among principle Miniſters; and this, he ſaith only to clear himſelf of Schiſm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, Pauls</hi> buiſineſs was chiefly to convert, and other Miniſters to baptize; much like the Text, <hi>John</hi> 4.2. <hi>Jeſus himſelf baptized not, but his Diſciples;</hi> and ſo there is no doubt, but the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving <hi>Corinthians</hi> were baptized, tho' not all by <hi>Paul;</hi> and ſo <hi>John</hi> 3.22.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="34" type="chapter">
            <pb n="46" facs="tcp:99244:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXIV. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> And were all baptized unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That as when believers are baptiſed, they publickly own Chriſt for their head &amp; leader; ſo the chil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ren or people of Iſrael paſſing with the cloud before and behind them; and through the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> they pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly declared <hi>Moſes</hi> to be their leader; ſo it was to them the diſtinguiſhing Sign or Ordinance, and that by God's Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they were all that obeyed the Lord by <hi>Moſes</hi> to paſs through the Sea.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> There is alſo reſemblance between dipping and being in the cloud, and in the ſea; for in both, the whole body is covere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, the cloud was before <hi>Iſrael</hi> and behind, and it reſted upon them; and they were in the cloud covered all over. And the Sea alſo was a reſemblance of dipping: for as they went u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on the bottom of the Sea, the waters were abundantly higher than their heads: and therefore it may be ſaid, they were in the depth of the Sea or in a ſenſe Dipt. For they were in the middle and at the bottom, (tho' the waters were miraculouſly made to ſtand from their Bodies, that they might not be drowned,) and Therefore and Apoſtle may ſay as this Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>And were all b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptized unto</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes <hi>in the cloud, and in the Sea.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="35" type="chapter">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:99244:25"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXV. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.13.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="13">
                     <hi>13.</hi> For by one ſpirit we are all baptiſed into one body, whether we be J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w or Gentile, whether we be bond or free, and have been all made to drink into one ſpirit.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That the Spirit that accompanys the Preaching of the Goſpel is one in all places, and to all Perſons that effectually believe, and becauſe of thus believing we believers were baptized into one Church. The Bride the Lambs Wife, part whereof were the viſible Saints at <hi>Corinth,</hi> to whom we were added by viſible demonſtration, baptiſm, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we were ſervants or free; all one, all alike, whether our Parents believing or unbelieving, ſo the Perſon baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were a believer, and have been all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the one Spirit in the one Body, the Church through the Spirit and ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiſm.</p>
            <p>Love to the Brethren is from the oneneſs of that one Spirit of God; <hi>and the multitude of them that believed, were of one heart, and of one Soul,</hi> Acts 4.32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Infants are not concerned in this All baptized; for Infants were not the <hi>Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thian</hi> Saints that this Epiſtle was writ to (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2.) nor were Infants bond ſervants, neither had Infants the comforts of the Spirit at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending Faith in our Lord Jeſus; for that Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit convinceth the world of ſin, and a ſoul, of the want of a Saviour; and alſo ſhews it the Chriſt that dyed not for his own ſins but others An Infant cannot believe this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Paul</hi> again numbereth himſelf among the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, and not among Infants.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="36" type="chapter">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:99244:26"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXVI. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.29</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20.</hi> Elſe what ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll th y <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o whi h are bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized for the Dead? If the Dead riſe not at all, why are they then bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ze<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> for the dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I <hi>Note,</hi> That in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his Chapter the Apoſtle is about to clear up the Reſurrection of the dead, and to do it, take<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the baptiſing of the Saints upon thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> believing to be one good Argument for it; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dingly argues thus: The Saints bapti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> dipping <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſignify the Death of Chriſt, &amp; riſing again out of the Water, to ſignify, the reſurrection of Chriſt, would ſignify nothing, if there was not indeed the Reſurrection of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody of Chriſt, nor is to be indeed a Reſurrection of the Saints, of whom Chriſt's Body was the fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Fruits. What ſignifies, (ſaith he to believers) your being baptized into, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon the Profeſſion of the Faith of the Death and Reſurrection of Chriſt, if Chriſt did not die, and riſe again; and if he aroſe again, then in time ſhall be a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of them that are his; the Bodies of the Saints being the purchaſe of the Blood of Chriſt, as well as their Souls.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> No Infants can be concerned in this Baptiſm, becauſe they could not be baptiſed for the dead; they could not believe nor confeſs that Chriſt died &amp; roſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again. That one dead, riſen Jeſus, ſhould ſatisfy the demands of infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Juſtice, for thouſands and millions of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Sinners, chief of Sinners, pall, preſent, &amp; to come, of which his Reſurrection being a diſcharge from the Priſon of Death, is a clear proof that he paid all the demands of injureſt Juſtice.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="37" type="chapter">
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:99244:26"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXVII. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="27">
                     <hi>27</hi> For as many of you as have been baptized into Christ, have put on Chriſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>The Apoſtle in this Chapter is ſhewing, that perſons in a ſtate of nature, are under the Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage &amp; ſoveraignty of the Law of Works, the holy, yet imperfect to juſtify a ſinner. <hi>Had there been a Law that could have given Life, Chriſt needed not to have died.</hi> But Saints by faith &amp; o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, are apparently Chriſt's Free-men.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I note that,</hi> As many as have upon profeſſion of the faith of the Goſpel been Baptized, have given a ſign of being changed from expectati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Juſtification by the Works of the Law, to <hi>an expectation of Juſtification by the Blood of Chriſt;</hi> &amp; ſo from a ſtate of nature to a ſtate of grace, &amp; that you <hi>Galathians</hi> have ſo declared, your being <hi>baptized upon prof ſſion of that Doctrine,</hi> is a ſufficient teſtimony; thus he goes on, expect not Juſtification by the Law, <hi>beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n not in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit &amp; end in the fleſh;</hi> now Baptiſm hath publick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinguiſhed you from the world, <hi>fight the good fight of Faith in the Son of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Infants never did put on Chriſt, for they never did, from a ſenſe of a change in <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> or <hi>faith</hi> in the Goſpel deſire Baptiſm; but on the contrary, are after their Sprinkling in a ſtate of nature, as every days <hi>experience</hi> proves by their ſigns of unregeneracy, &amp; the continual <hi>preſſing</hi> that preachers make to <hi>turn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> As a Noble man's Servant is put in <hi>his Lords Livery to be kn wn thereby,</hi> ſo <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers Baptiſm is</hi> a <hi>piece of the Livery of the Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="38" type="chapter">
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:99244:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXVIII. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.4.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="4">
                     <hi>4.</hi> One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note that,</hi> As here is but one Baptiſm, ſo it ought to be Continued as it was begun by <hi>Dipping of Believers,</hi> for there is but <hi>one Baptiſm</hi> appointed as an <hi>Ordinance</hi> in the Church, &amp; as for <hi>Sprinkling of Infants,</hi> it is without any Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample or order from <hi>Chriſt</hi> or his Apoſtles; &amp; therefore that cannot be <hi>Baptiſm;</hi> ſo that there being but one baptiſm, that baptiſm muſt be Dipping of Believers.</p>
            <p>The nature and end of the Ordinance proves, That Baptizing is Dipping, and not Sprinkling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To be a ſign of the Covenant on Gods part, <hi>viz. Of waſhing away of ſin, cleanſing the whole man,</hi> like the cleanſing in the Law <hi>Lev.</hi> 15.5. <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To Figure out the Covenant on man's part, that he thereby viſibly declares to enter into, <hi>viz. to die to ſin, and live to Chriſt in newneſs of Life, by that figurative Death, Burial and Reſurrection, by being put under the water, &amp; Raiſed up again,</hi> Rom. 6.4. Col. 2.11, 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Third<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> To ſeparate the Church from the World.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To convince the Baptiſed that they are engaged by their own act of Baptiſm, as their <hi>laying their hands to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>low</hi> to hold out to the end.</p>
            <p>Therefore Infant Sprinkling muſt be an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of worldly wiſe men, whoſe wiſdom is fooliſhneſs with God; and ſo it is a profanation of the holy Ordinance of Baptiſm, and only Will Worſhip, like <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zza</hi>'s touching the Ark of God, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6.6 when another way of ſervice was preſcribed. <hi>Numb.</hi> 4.6.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="39" type="chapter">
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:99244:27"/>
            <head>CHAP. XXXIX. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="12">
                     <hi>12.</hi> Buried with him <hi>(Chriſt)</hi> in Baptiſm where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo ye are riſen with him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note, that</hi> Baptiſm is a Burying in the Water, and a riſing again out of the Water, whereby the baptized ſhew, that Chriſt was buried, and aroſe again; <hi>Or thus, That as the baptized, tho buried in the Water, riſeth again, ſo Chriſt tho buried in the Earth, did not lye long, but aroſe again.</hi> But ſprinkling cannot be this ſign of being Buried and riſen.</p>
            <p>A man above-ground cannot be ſaid to be buried, becauſe he hath a little Duſt thrown in his face, neither can Sprinkling be a ſign of burying with Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Several Scripture Metaphors explain Baptizing to be Dipping.</p>
            <p>When Perſons are over-whelmed in great ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erings, they are ſaid to be baptized therein, <hi>Mat</hi> 20.22, 23. <hi>Luke</hi> 12.5. When they have great meaſures of the ſpirit, they are ſaid to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized with the ſpirit, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.5. When the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were covered with a <hi>Cloud,</hi> and the Sea on both ſides, they were then ſaid to be Baptized in the Sea and in the Cloud, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. with <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.12. When <hi>Aſhur</hi> had the promiſed bleſſing of great plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, he is ſaid to have his feet dipt in Oyl.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>As the ignorant World lays up a human Faith, or inherent Holineſs, they alſo lay up a Human Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm or Infant Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as Saints have many things of ſelf, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually apt to put in with Chriſts perfection, ſo ſomethings do mingle with their duties, and one is Infant Sprinkling.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="40" type="chapter">
            <pb n="52" facs="tcp:99244:28"/>
            <head>CHAP. XL. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.1, 2.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">
                     <hi>1.</hi> — Not laying again the foundation of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance from dead Works, &amp; of faith towards God.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Of the Doctrine of Baptiſm, and laying on of Hands, and of the Reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrection of the Dead, and of eternal Judgment.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note that,</hi> Baptiſm was a Doctrine left in charge to the Church, and that it follows in order in the Third place, after Repentance &amp; Faith; and that it is here reckoned a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation Principal. Then any with Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derment may ſay, who dares move this Foundation that the Father, Son, and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit have thus laid for Believers? they only being capable to enter into a Viſible Covenant with Jeſus Chriſt; for Baptiſm is an Ordinance for the Solemnization of the Soul's Viſible Marriage Union with Chriſt, <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. Other Foundations can no man lay then what is already laid.</p>
            <p>The man of ſin, the Miſtery of iniquity, the great Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> hath rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the Church of Chriſt of the names of her Ordinances, and put them upon her Whoriſh Inventions, that ſhe may deceive the Nations therewith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> Sprinkling will not ſerve inſtead of Dipping, becauſe it is a ſin to alter what God our moſt wiſe Soveraign hath appointed in his Worſhip, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 24.5 <hi>Obedience is better than Sacrifice,</hi> do as you are bid.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="41" type="chapter">
            <pb n="53" facs="tcp:99244:28"/>
            <head>CHAP. XLI. 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 3.20, 21.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p n="20">
                     <hi>20</hi> — <hi>Noah</hi> whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e the Ark was preparing, wherein f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w, that is, right Souls were ſav'd by water</p>
                  <p n="21">
                     <hi>21.</hi> The like Figure whereunto even Baptiſm doth alſo now ſave us (not the putting away the filth of the fleſh, but the anſwer of a good Conſcience towards God) by the Reſurrection of Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>us Christ.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>I note that,</hi> A Believer by being baptized, is obedient to God's Will, as <hi>Noah</hi> was obedient in building the Ark, and going into it to his ſaving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, Baptiſm</hi> (ſaith <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>doth now ſave us by the Reſurrection of Christ;</hi> which is as to ſay, our <hi>believers baptiſm</hi> being <hi>our anſwer of a good co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcience towards God,</hi> is a ſign of our <hi>Sanct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and ſo Dipping being an effect of our Sanctification, doth now ſave us by the power of the eternal, Spirit that wrought that ſanctification, which <hi>Sanctification</hi> is the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification for heaven; and ſo <hi>we are kept</hi> (ſanctified) <hi>by the mighty power of God to Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> began and continued by <hi>Christ</hi>'s ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of which his Reſurrection was a ſign.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again, Noah</hi> by Water dyed to the old world and lived to the new, as the baptized believer dies to ſin, wherein he once delighted, and lives to Righteouſneſs; or thus, dead to the ſufficiency of the Law, upon which he once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended, &amp; alive to the ſufficiency of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> There is alſo a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ind of likeneſs between <hi>Noah's Flood</hi> &amp; the water of Baptiſm, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cauſe both is much Water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> The Apoſtle ſaying, ſaved by water, ſeems as it were, a pointing at the Text, <hi>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:99244:29"/>
            <head>The Concluſion reſpecting the Perſons that are to be Baptized.</head>
            <p>Now I have noted o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orty Texts con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erein are variety of perſons mentioned as <hi>Jeruſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gion</hi> roun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> about <hi>Jor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> that confeſt their ſins; <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſus</hi> himſelf. Jeſus made and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized <hi>more Diſcip es</hi> than <hi>John; Three Thouſand</hi> Souls that gladly received the Word. And they of <hi>Samaria</hi> believing <hi>Philip</hi> were baptiz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, both <hi>Men and Women,</hi> the <hi>Eunuch; Paul; They</hi> that received the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Lydia,</hi> the <hi>Jaylor;</hi> and <hi>they</hi> that believed of their Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Criſpus. Corinthians</hi> hearing believed, <hi>Epeſians</hi> that were baptized by <hi>John; Romans, Gains, Stephanus;</hi> believing <hi>Corinthians, Gala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thians, Epeſians, Colloſians, Hebrews,</hi> and thoſe that have the anſwer of a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>Whereby <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elivers Baptiſm</hi> is clearly proved.</p>
            <p>And I find not one word, command, nor example, throughout the <hi>New Testament</hi> for <hi>Infant Sprinkling</hi> or Baptizing before ſigns of Repentance, tho here are ſo many ſorts of perſons mentioned, deſcribed and named, yet no Infant. Whereby <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> muſt of neceſſity be indee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ordinance required by the <hi>Lord Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the <hi>Authority</hi> of forty <hi>New Teſtament</hi> Texts is not, convincing and ſwaying with thoſe that would live Godly, or be reputed <hi>Christians,</hi> I know not what Argument will.</p>
            <p>Where <hi>Scripture</hi> will not prevail, people will remain in unbelief, <hi>Tho one riſe from the dead.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:99244:29"/>
            <head>The Concluſion reſpecting the Mode or manner of Baptiſm.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt according to his Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion <hi>baptized</hi> in the <hi>Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r Jordan, Mat.</hi> 3 4. <hi>Jeſas came from Gallil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to the River</hi> Jordan <hi>to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> baptized;</hi> and when baptized, <hi>Went up ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> got way o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t of the water. Mark</hi> 1.5. All <hi>baptized in the River</hi> Jor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an, <hi>and Jeſus was baptized in</hi> Jorda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Mark</hi> 1.9. <hi>John</hi> 3.23. <hi>John was baptizing in</hi> Enon, <hi>becauſe there was much water there. And they went down both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the water, both</hi> Philip <hi>and the</hi> Eunuch, <hi>and he baptized him. And when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey were come up out of the water,</hi> &amp;c. Acts 8.38, 39. And <hi>Acts</hi> 10.48 Peter <hi>commanded them to be Baptized;</hi> ſaid <hi>Ananias</hi> to <hi>Paul, Ariſe and be baptized, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhing a way thy ſins. We are buried with</hi> Chriſt <hi>by baptiſm, Rom.</hi> 6.4, 5. <hi>If we have been planted together with him in the</hi> likeneſs <hi>of his death. And were all baptized to</hi> Moſes <hi>in the Cloud, and in the Sea,</hi> 1 Cor. 10.2. <hi>One Lord, one Faith, one Baptiſm,</hi> Eph 4.5. <hi>Buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm, wherein alſo ye are riſen with him,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.12.</p>
            <p>'Tis ſtrange and unaccountable, that any man ſhould pretend to draw a concluſion of Infant Sprin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling from Scripture, when there's not a Text that looks like it. And more ſtrange that any ſhould draw a concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that <hi>Infant Sprinkling</hi> is <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> when all the Texts about <hi>Baptiſm</hi> tends to prove, and clear the Dipping of <hi>Believers</hi> only.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="history">
            <pb n="56" facs="tcp:99244:30"/>
            <head>How Infant Sprinkling came in faſhion.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>The Church of</hi> Rome <hi>co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>feſſeth, ſhe changed Dipping into Sprinkling;</hi> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>prian <hi>is the firſt who pleads for baptiſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g the Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k by Sprinkling, and for Sprinkling now Converts in the Priſon-houſe; and by degrees they brought it in for ſick Children then for all Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Romes</hi> firſt and great Argument, by which <hi>Infants Baptiſm</hi> was brought in, was their imagining, it took away original Sin; upon which they made this Canon in the <hi>Milevetan</hi> Cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is our Will, that all who affirm Young Children have everlaſting life, which are not baptized, to the taking away of Original Sin, ſhall be Anathemized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So the fifth Council at <hi>Carthage,</hi> 416.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We will that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hoſoever denyeth that little Children by Baptiſm, are not freed from Perdition and eternally ſaved, that they be ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was firſt confi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> by Pope <hi>Innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> and <hi>Augustin,</hi> with ſeventy Biſhops.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I note,</hi> Thus a Chriſtian may ſee the <hi>Our Will,</hi> &amp; the <hi>We Will,</hi> that brought in <hi>nfant Sprinkling</hi> without God's Will, &amp; therefore 'tis not ſtrange if ſome Infants in cold Countries, Dye, if Dipt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> The <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>declined Church</hi> were but <hi>Children</hi> in compariſon of the <hi>Apost<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Apoſtles ſhall be my Fathers.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="discussion">
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:99244:30"/>
            <head>The Evil Tendencies and Conſequences of Infant Sprinkling.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> It hath been a Snare to moſt people, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they do thereby reckon themſelves to be Chriſtians, and in a Salvable Condition, <hi>tho' they indeed are without Faith and Repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2ly.</hi> It hath been the Root and off ſpring of the National Churches, and is eſſential to their ſtanding.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3ly.</hi> The National Sprinklers of Infants have often made War, upon the Congregational, Chriſtians for obſerving the word of God, as the only rule of Faith and Practice.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4ly.</hi> It greatly indangers <hi>Congr gational Churches</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egenerate, and become <hi>National,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5ly.</hi> It is one of the great ſupports of the Anti Chriſtian Whore of <hi>Babilon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y.</hi> There is more app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>opriated to Infant Sprinkling, then is due to Goſpel Baptiſm, <hi>Tak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away Original ſi, &amp; Qualifying for Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>7ly.</hi> It ſets aſide Gods command and puts Men upon the quite contrary, by which rule alſo any other Erronious thing may come in.</p>
            <p n="8">
               <hi>8ly.</hi> To guard Infants Sprinkling, many Men bar the unſprinkled Infants out of Heaven, <hi>&amp; ſo their way Damn Millions that are ſaved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <hi>9ly.</hi> It puts ſome men upon aſerting that all Infants of believers are in covenant. And yet ſay, that <hi>there is no falling from a State of Grace,</hi> Tho on the contrary, they will acknowledge <hi>that many of the believers Sprinkled, Infants living to maturity die unregenerated, &amp; periſh eternally,</hi> Evils always attend Error, &amp; here are nine.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="objections">
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:99244:31"/>
            <head>The Objections that the ignorant world and others uſually make againſt Believers Baptiſm are Anſwered.</head>
            <p>Obj. 1. <hi>I have been baptiſed in my Infancy; therefore, what need I be baptiſed again?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You was but <hi>Rantiſed,</hi> or Sprinkled, not Dipt nor Baptiſed, <hi>John</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>Obj. 2. <hi>Learned men are for Infant Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Some Learned men are for <hi>Popery</hi> not for <hi>Purity.</hi> But all are not; however the Goſpel ought not to ſubmit to learned Men, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.19.</p>
            <p>Obj. 3. <hi>Whole F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es were baptized.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> All that were baptized did firſt believe, <hi>Acts</hi> 16.34. Let it be ſo now.</p>
            <p>Obj. 4. <hi>Circumciſion availeth nothing, but a n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>w Creature; then what need I be baptized?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You may as well infer and ſay, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God will ſave by grace, that therefore you will take the liberty of forbearing good Works, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1.15. or becauſe <hi>God</hi> works, you will play.</p>
            <p>Ob. 5. <hi>Many lays too much ſtreſs upon beleivers baptiſm, and that makes us the more backward to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And I fear you lay too little. Chriſt layeth it thus: <hi>He that Believeth and is bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized ſhall be ſaved,</hi> Mark 16.16.</p>
            <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>j. 6. <hi>Were not little Children baptized by Christ Mark</hi> 10.13, 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, he only bleſt them, <hi>Mark</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>0.16.</p>
            <p>Obj. 7. <hi>Infa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t baptiſm is not forbidden.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> At that door Popiſh Error comes in; and all others may: yet what's not appointed, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> forbidden, <hi>Lev.</hi> 10.2, 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <pb n="59" facs="tcp:99244:31"/>
            <p> Obj. 8. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Nations are to be baptized, and Infants are part of Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But they ſhould be taught firſt an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> believe, acco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding to the ſame Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.16. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.12.</p>
            <p>Obj. 9. <hi>There hath been bad Men</hi> Anabaptiſts</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Shew me a Profeſſion that hath not ſuch, nay, the many Malefactors that hath ſuffer Death in your memory have been of other Religions, and it may be of your Church, but what is that to Religion it ſelf? <hi>Judas</hi> being a <hi>Judas,</hi> doth not overthrow the Goſpel; 'tis not perſons but things that are the Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the Goſpel; we are upon even Believing and Dipping</p>
            <p>Obj. 10. <hi>Infant Priviledges are not leſs under the Goſpel, then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er the Law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Their ſaving Priviledges are the ſame but that gives no ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ht to Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>Obj. 11. <hi>Baptiſm came in the room of Circumciſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Circumciſion of the heart came in the room of Circumciſion of the fleſh, <hi>Rom.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.28.29. the priviledges wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to Circumciſion, but now it is to Believing</p>
            <p>Obj. 12. <hi>There's an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Conſent of Churches and An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y for Inf nt Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Such couſ n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> makes nothing true nor f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lſe; 'tis Scripture d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s both before Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent had a Being, as it was in the beginning, ſhould be now, and a Believer Baptized, may ſay, is now, and ever ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll be.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>There are ſome other Objections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> One Rule will anſwer all Objections againſt Believers Baptiſm, <hi>viz That,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God will ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ept <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>thing in his Worſhip but what be hath appointed.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="objections">
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:99244:32"/>
            <head>The Objections that ſome Chriſtians make, are here Anſwered.</head>
            <p>Obj. 14. <hi>Believers Children are holy,</hi> 1 Cor. 7.14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> A Believers unbelieving Husband or Wife hath the ſame holineſs by the ſame text.</p>
            <p>Obj. 15. <hi>Infants were once Church members.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> So were ſervants too Godly or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, a National Church was once <hi>of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine appointment,</hi> but neither now, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17.</p>
            <p>Obj. 16. <hi>Three thouſand perſons could not be dipt in one day! therefore they were ſprinkled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No: Three thouſand may be almoſt if not altogether as ſoon Dipt as Sprinkled, and there was about four-ſcore Preaching Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to do the Work.</p>
            <p>Obj. 17. <hi>There is as much command for Infants bapt. as for Womens p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rtaking of the Lord's Supper.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, there is not: for it is ſaid, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.28. <hi>Let a man,</hi> &amp;c. The <hi>Greek</hi> word here is of the common Gender, and includes both Sexes. <hi>Conſider</hi> Acts 1.13. Gen. 2.17.</p>
            <p>Obj. 18. <hi>The Promiſe is to the Seed of Believers,</hi> Acts 2.39.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The promiſe here intended was, that if the Holy Ghoſt in <hi>Joel</hi> 2.32. which they might expect, and alſo their poſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erity, and the Gentiles upon their effectual Calling: So that their believing is upon their Calling, which may be their b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ptiſm.</p>
            <p>Obj. 19. <hi>Children of Believers have habitual faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The whole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ible doth not afford one word of habitual Faith in Infants, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 17. <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:99244:32"/>
            <p> Obj. 20. <hi>If the Root be holy, then are the branches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Saints do not beget ſaints, <hi>John</hi> 3.6. <hi>John</hi> 1.13. <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.1. <hi>(believers)</hi> are created in Chriſt Jeſus, He is the Root, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.7. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.10. He is made unto us Sanctification. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30</p>
            <p>Obj. 21. <hi>Baptiſm is the Seal of the Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> You Seal without God's Seal or Directions, and can no where find his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation or Covenant Priviledge thereby, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.10. to 20.</p>
            <p>Obj. 22. <hi>Some Children are in the Covenant,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> What then, Chriſt and his Apoſtles knew that as well as you, but yet never ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them; 2dly. You know not which are more than others; 3dly. Why may not you put the Lord's Supper upon them too?</p>
            <p>Obj. 23 <hi>Neceſſary and unavoidable Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences will prove Infant Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> We could never yet ſee theſe Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and unavoidable Conſequences; and it is impoſſible that any man, that hath not before-hand heard of Infant Sprinkling, ſhould ever find it by reading the Scriptures; but believers baptiſm is there apparent.</p>
            <p>Whether is beſt to ground our Faith upon a poſitive command or a ſuppoſed conſequence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> Let men ſay what they will by way of Objection, yet unleſs they can take out of the <hi>New Teſtament</hi> the Texts about <hi>Baptiſm,</hi> theſe Texts will continually as great Guns, be battering down <hi>Infant Sprinkling</hi> as a Rampart of that great City M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſtery <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Precept and Practice in about forty Texts of Scripture for <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="6 letters">
                     <desc>••••••</desc>
                  </gap>ers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> is a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Anſwer to any Objection.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="differences">
            <pb n="62" facs="tcp:99244:33"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The differences between</hi> Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm <hi>and</hi> Infants Sprinkling.</head>
            <p n="1">1. God hath promiſed that he that <hi>Believeth and is Baptiſed,</hi> ſhall be ſaved, <hi>Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k</hi> 16.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But there's no promiſes ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xed to Infant Sprinkl.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a lively ſimilitude between believers being buried in the Water, riſing again, and Chriſts Death, Burial, and reſurrection, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling ſhews no likeneſs to either.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Believers Bap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſed</hi> are entere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> into a <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed</hi> way of Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vation, (profeſſion, Viſible Sanctification or a holy Life,) and ſo are likely to be ſaved, <hi>John</hi> 5.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Spri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kled are not, but remain as they were by nature Children of Wrath,</hi> Eph. 2.3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Believers Baptiſed,</hi> Love God and keep his Commandeme ts <hi>John</hi> 14 15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Sprinkled do not Love God, nor keep his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Teaching, Repenting, <hi>Beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving before Baptiſing,</hi> is Chriſts command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>8.18, 19.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Sprinkling of Infants, is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptizing believers is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ptizing Christians But baptizi g I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fants is not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Believers baptiſm</hi> hath no contradictions attending the Practi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Inf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t Sprink ing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h many Contradi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ters aſſert, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſprinkling is a Tok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ent Reg ne ation, tho th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n nor in after time a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y ſig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of a Change in Nature ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears in the In<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:99244:33"/> 2. <hi>A Sign of Death, Burial, Reſurrection, tho they do not dip, bury, raiſe again, but ſprinkle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Proteſtants S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>perate from</hi> Rome, <hi>as the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lſe Church, and yet ſome own Popih Priests Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, effectual Baptiſm, as into one</hi> &amp; <hi>the ſame Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Some profeſs that there is no falling from Grace on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e received, and that that Grace is in an Infant Sprinkled; Yet they afterwards teach for their Converſion; and in caſe of ſigns of final unbelief, reject them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Believers baptiſed,</hi> of right come to the Lord's Table, <hi>Asts</hi> 2.41 42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants ſprinkled come neither right nor wrong.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> hath a commiſſion &amp; a command, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18, 19. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.46, 47, 48.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling hath neither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Believers Bapt</hi> hath Scripture Examples <hi>But Infant Sprinkling</hi> hath none.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> was preached by Chriſt and his Apoſtles, as part of the Counſel of God, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3 6. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.27.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling never was.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="12">12 <hi>Believers baptiſm</hi> was owned by God, his Son Jeſus, and the holy Spirit viſibly deſcending from Heaven, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Sprinkling never was ſo owned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Believ. bapt.</hi> is upon their Acting Faith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants act no Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="14">14. <hi>Believers baptized, have</hi> the Anſwer of a good Conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants have not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="15">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:99244:34"/> 15. <hi>Believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs Baptiſm</hi> may be ſeale<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>Martyr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om,</hi> becauſe warranted by Gods Word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Sprink ing may not, becauſe not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Believers Baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was the Publican's glorifying God, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.29</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Sprinkling never was ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Believers Baptiſm,</hi> if rejected, 'tis the rejecting the Counſel of God, and againſt themſelves, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But not ſo of Infant Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Believers baptiſm</hi> agrees with all <hi>Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fants Sprinkling agrees with none.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Believ. Bapt</hi> directs to much water, <hi>Joh</hi> 3.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants Sprinkling hath but little.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="20">20. To <hi>baptize Believers,</hi> is to keep the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances as they were delivered, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to ſprinkle Infants, is to take that which never was delivered.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="21">21. To <hi>baptize Believers,</hi> is no change of God's Ordinance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to ſprinkle Infants is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Believers baptized</hi> upon their own Faith, are in the right way to ſalvation, <hi>John</hi> 10.28.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants ſprinkled upon the Faith of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, are not in the right way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Believers baptiſm,</hi> is its being an Act of the Judgment, Choice, Will and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to Worſhip God, <hi>John</hi> 4.24.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling is not ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Believers Bapi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſm</hi> hath the beſt Antiquity to plead, being as Old as <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling hath started up ſince.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="25">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:99244:34"/> 25. All thoſe who ſprinkle Infants, do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that believers were baptiz'd by the <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But all thoſe who baptize believers only, do deny that any Infants were baptized by the Apoſtles?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="26">26. Believers dipt, know they were baptiz'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants don't know they were ſprinkled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27 They that baptize believers, are ſure that there is a Faith profeſſed by them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But 'tis otherways of Sprinkling Infants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="28">28. Believers baptiſed act in Obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants ſprinkled act not at all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="29">29. Believers baptiſm hath no abſurdities in't.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling hath ſeveral,</hi> Viz.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>That Regeneration may be apparent before calling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>hat Church-memberſhip before converſions a duty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That one may be baptized by anothers faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That National Churches are more agreeable to the Goſpel than Congregation<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>That a carnal Seed hath a ſpiritual Right.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Antichriſtian hath Authority to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter Christian Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="30">30. Of believers baptiſm, God will not ſay, Who hath required theſe things at your hands?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But of Infant Sprinklirg he may ſay ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="31">31. Believers Baptiſm will ſtand as long as God's Word ſtands, becauſe ſupported thereby, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.18.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkling muſt fall for want of it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="32">32. Believers baptized, do believe, repent, examine themſelves, make judgment of things, love one another, take up Chriſt's Croſs, Watch and Pray, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore are fit Members of a Goſpel Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut Infants ſprinkled do not do ſo, and are not fit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="33">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:99244:35"/> 33. Believers baptiſm hath God's word for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant Sprinkl. hath only human conſequence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="34">34. That b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lievers were baptiſed by the Apoſtles, all Chriſtians may affirm.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But that Infants were ſprinkled by them, none can.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="35">35. In <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> when the <hi>Minister</hi> dippeth and ſaith, I baptize thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he ſpeaketh Truth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But in Infants ſprinkling, when the Miniſter ſprinkleth, and ſaith, I baptize thee,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>he ſpeaketh an untruth at least.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="36">36. <hi>Believers baptized,</hi> are taught of God, and made his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.18. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infants ſprinkled are neither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="37">37. To Believers baptiſm ſubmitted the L. Jeſus</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But to Infants Sprinkling never any like him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="38">38. <hi>Believers baptiſm</hi> introduceth no Error nor falſe Doctrine into the world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Infant ſprinkli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g introduceth many Errors.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That it taketh away Original ſin.</item>
               <item>2. That it worketh grace and regeneration.</item>
               <item>3. That it effects ſalvation by the work done</item>
               <item>4. That it is an Apoſtolical Tradition.</item>
               <item>5. That Infants have Faith.</item>
               <item>6. That Infants are D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcipl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>7. That <hi>only believers children</hi> are in <hi>Covenant</hi>
               </item>
               <item>8. It polluteth the Church with Mingling the World and Church together.</item>
               <item>9. Many deceitful and crafty Inventions of Antichriſt, as Goſſips, Biſhoping, Croſſings, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>10. It hath made contention in the Church.</item>
               <item>11. It hath cauſed the bloodſhed of Saints.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="contradiction">
            <pb n="67" facs="tcp:99244:35"/>
            <head>Chriſtian People's Self-Contradiction by Infant Sprinkling.</head>
            <p>TIs ſtrange, that a people <hi>(my Brethern in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her Doctrines)</hi> that have prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and contended for the Scriptures to be the only Rule of Faith and worſhip <hi>(and in other caſes, wi l ſay where is it written)</hi> ſhould be fond of Infant Sprinkling, for which they cannot find in Scripture any word, Command, nor Example for to give it the Reputation of a Church Ordinance.</p>
            <p>I profeſs, I muſt give away my Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, if I conſent to a Scriptureleſs Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance under the Name of a Scripture Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance: Never l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t me nor other Chriſtians pretend to bear a Teſtimony to the Truth, by ſuffering Perſecution, if Scripture muſt not be my Rule of Underſtanding and Faith, take away this and take all I have, or all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves have ſaid in order to Chriſtianity, or relating to Regeneration and Salvation.</p>
            <p>Can any Man ſpeak againſt Popery or Superſtition that will form a Principall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance in the Church without Scripture Authority for it; 'tis ſelf Contradiction ſo to do; 'Tis but pulling down one <hi>Babel</hi> and Building another.</p>
            <p>Let him that would find the truth of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm,</hi> ſearch the Scriptures, and there he may find that 'tis believers Dipping.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discussion">
            <pb n="68" facs="tcp:99244:36"/>
            <head>A ſight of a Believer at Baptizing.</head>
            <p>When you ſee a <hi>believer</hi> at <hi>baptiſing,</hi> you may know that <hi>Now he devides the time of his Life,</hi> that whereas from his birth to <hi>this time</hi> of his Baptiſm, he lived without giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Goſpelly appointed Sign of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving in the Lord Jeſus: But now he will live ſo no longer.</p>
            <p>He till now lived as the Ignorant <hi>Infant ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rinkled World</hi> that gives no ſigns of ſpecial believing, by ſpecial obedience to this call of the Lord Jeſus in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>But now the Believer is baptized, &amp; that of choice in obedience, and according to his Lord Jeſus's requirement; he declares to every body that he is a believer, a believer in the ſufficien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Lord Jeſus to ſave; and that he will no longer live as the Unregenerate do, without the further Sign of his Faith by his Goſpel Obedience. But will, as you ſee, <hi>by baptiſm, divide the Time of his l fe,</hi> that he may now ſay, <hi>let the time p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e for a vain Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tion;</hi> a careleſs, fearful, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> diſobedient Converſation. And may alſo from this time ſay, <hi>the life that I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w live is by Faith in the Son of God.</hi> My baptiſm upon beli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ving, is a doing that the Goſpel requires; for a beginning of a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ife of Faith, &amp; undergoing the Reproach of the world, for the ſake of my Lord the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ying Jeſus of <hi>Nazareth,</hi> our exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Saviour.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discussion">
            <pb n="69" facs="tcp:99244:36"/>
            <head>Of Reproaches and Sufferings.</head>
            <p>HIſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affords Relations of many peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in all Ages, ſince the firſt plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat on of the Goſpel, that have ſuffer'd Contempt, Reproach, Scandal, Lyes, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, cru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, miſery, Impriſonment, Death, and pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ick Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tyrdom, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot only for the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſing the Doct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of the Goſpel in general, but in pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ticular, for the Doctrin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of believ rs Baptiſm.</p>
            <p>And that which ſeems more ſtrange, is that thoſe Men who have been the moſt bitter Enemies to the purity of the Goſpel, have in all Ages been perſons not ſlighting or diſpiſing Religion, but thoſe that have made great pretentions to Religion, all of the ſame Spirit as were the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees, that under a ſhow of Sanctity, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented the ſufferings and Death of the Prophets, and paid a kind of Devotion to the place where they were laid, and built their Sepulchers, and yet as their Fathers did, ſo did they ſtill go on with Perſecution. And ever ſince the ſevere minded People upon account of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, have been the Prieſtly People; Nay what is worſe, a Reformed People have been as Ridgid as the former.</p>
            <p>Behold! a Wonder, <hi>a Buſh burning and not conſumed,</hi> Exod. 3.3. <hi>and Moſes ſaid, I will turn aſide, and ſet this great ſight,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>God's lively Emblem of the Aflicted, Perſecuted Church of Chriſt.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="discussion">
            <pb n="70" facs="tcp:99244:37"/>
            <head>The Dignity of the Lord Jeſus, that Baptiſed Believers obey.</head>
            <p>The <hi>Mighty Jeſus</hi> is the <hi>God man,</hi> ſaith <hi>God</hi> the Father, <hi>The Man that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y Fellow,</hi> Zach. 13. 7. <hi>His Name ſhall be called the</hi> wonderful Counſellor, <hi>the mighty</hi> God, <hi>the everlaſting</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>the Prince of peace, Iſaiah,</hi> 9.6.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Who is the I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>age of the Inviſible God, the firſt born of every Creature. Col.</hi> 1.15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For by</hi> him <hi>were all things created that are in Heaven, and that are in Earth, viſible and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, whether they be Thrones or Dominions, or Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities, or Powers, all things were created by him and for him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He is before all things, and by him all things conſiſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And</hi> he <hi>is the head of the Body the Church, who is the beginning, the first born from she dead, that in all things he might have the preheminence. For it pleaſed the Father, that in him ſhould all fulneſs dwell. And (having made Peace through the Blood of his Croſs) by him, to reconcile all things to himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Beware leſt any ſpoil you through Philoſophy and vain deceit, after the Traditions of Men, after the Rudiments of the World, and not after Christ. For in</hi> him <hi>dwelleth all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily.</hi> Col. 2.8, 9. Rom. 9.5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Feed the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his own blood,</hi> Acts 20.28. Phil. 2.6.</p>
            <p>Who <hi>being the brightneſs of his Glory, and the expreſs Image of his perſon, and upholding all things by the word of his power, when he had by himſelf purged our ſins, ſate down on the Right hand of the Majesty on high,</hi> Heb. 1.3.</p>
            <p>Why ſhould not the mighty Jeſus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Obey'd?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="71" facs="tcp:99244:37"/>
            <head>The Concluſion.</head>
            <p>SIn-ſick Soul, haſt thou fallen in love with the Lord Jeſus, and would'ſt have God give thee an Emblem, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.5. of his pardoning Grace to make thee well? Why here it is; here is upon thy Believing, much Water <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.23. aſſigned thee in his Ordinance of Baptiſm. A River of Water, enough to cover thee all over, to dive in, to ſwim in. Then wouldſt thou now, if thou hadſt thy choice of an Emblem of the pardoning Grace of God thou wants, chooſe a few drops of Water, or enough to cover thee all over <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? I dare ſay, thy Wants being great, thou wouldſt chooſe enough to cover thee all over. Then thank God he hath done it to thy hand, and that above a thouſand years ago, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thou thoughteſt of either thy ſelf or thy ſin, or thy God: Yea, thy Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus hath given his Apoſtles Commiſſion to Dip thee in much Water, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19, 20. to let thee know, that he hath according to thy Wants and deſire, Grace enough and to ſpare, not juſt enough and no more, but abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ore than thou needeſt; here is a Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ep River, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.5. therefore fear not wanting, he'll not ſparingly Sprinkle thee, as if his grace would ſpend too faſt to hold out, or was too coſtly to beſtow upon thee? No, but he'll by Dipping liberally waſh thee clean in the flowing ſtreams <hi>of the River of Water of Life.</hi> O the heighth of the Water and the depth, <hi>Ezek</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.14. Chap 34.18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.18. of the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Life (Grace) for thy preſervation, and Salvation, Chriſt is full, free and unſearchable, then how ſhould a few
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:99244:38"/>drops of Water ſignifie his Grace, ſo well as abundance? What's a few Sparks to ſet forth the Glory of the Meridian Sun, or a few drops of Water to ſhew the abundance of the Ocean Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, with the unaccountable <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lowing motions and ſwellings thereof, with its ability to ſuſtain the mighty Creatures therein? Nothing: no drops ſo proper as a River to illuſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; The ſtreams of Grace the flowin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>race; <hi>Pſal</hi> 147.8. the abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Grace; the freeneſs and full<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs of Grace; the Floo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Grace; the irreſiſtible force and runnings of Grace; Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> boying, float<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Long-ſuff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ring nature of Grace. A grace-built Soul can never ſink through, or be drowned in grace: O aſtoniſhing grace! the Ocean of Grace is as Infinite as any other divine Attribute, and conſtrains the greateſt Sinners, a prodigious ſort and ſize of ſinners have lived. <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.14. yea lived forever by grace, then what's a few drops of Water to ſet forth the Infiniteneſs of the Divine Attribute of grace; O grace! like the Ocean, runs round all the Nations of the World; grace like the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eepeth the World ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; grace like the Ocean flows Night and Day, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hou ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or waking; grace like a River <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> always in motion. Grace like a River runs many miles to water the Countries, and ſuſtain the Lives of thirſty Creatures, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.2. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.1. Grace like a River runs in the lowley Valleys, the humble ſouls: Grace like a River carrieth away the daily filth of ſin, Saints ſin, and keepeth them ſweet and clean: And as moſt people deſire to build their Houſes and Towns by the River that they may be ſupplyed and ſuſtained by the waters
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:99244:38"/>thereof, ſo the ſoul that is converted, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to live by grace, to build it's houſe by grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.3. the Rive of Grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.4. <hi>the streams whereof ſhall make glad the City of God.</hi> See therefore, pretious ſoul, here's Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon enough, That grace by the Wiſdom of God ſhould be compared to much Water, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.5, to 12. and that a River ſhould be more proper for Believers Baptiſm than a few drops, <hi>John</hi> 3.23. becauſe thy ſoul wants (and that God and thy ſelf knoweſt) abundance of grace, yea the continual flowing grace. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 116.3, 4.</p>
            <p>Grace, abounding over flowing ſaving grace, hath like the Ocean's flowing twice in twenty four hours, puzled the worldly Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to find out the reaſon of it: It is <hi>to the Iews a stumbling block, and to the greeks foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſs,</hi> but yet God in ſaving by grace acts like himſelf, in a way of wiſdom, to preſerve his ſoveraignty, and glorify all his Attributes, &amp; ſo he doth by aſſigning Believers Dipping in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, to be an Emblem of his much grace to a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever <hi>Acts</hi> 22.16. <hi>Ioel</hi> 3.18. <hi>Mich.</hi> 7.16. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Job</hi> 49.2. <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.13. <hi>Zech.</hi> 14.8. <hi>John</hi> 4.14.</p>
            <p>But why muſt people come to the water, and not the water be brought to them in Gods Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Baptiſm? Why, it may be it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe much water is needful for dipping, and it may be alſo to ſhew, that grace is not at mans will; <hi>Job</hi> 22.17. and that grace, waſhing, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, ſaving grace, is to keep its place; for grace hath a dignity 'tis ſaid, to reign <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.21. as a King; &amp; a King will keep his ſoveraignty, &amp; Grace is alſo called <hi>a River of water of Life,</hi> Rev. 22.1.2.17. And you know, a River will keep it's place <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.9. And ſo, tho God hath a River of grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.9. yet it runs its own courſe, here
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:99244:39"/>and their, and one man for another is not permitted to take it out of it's Channel, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 104.10. but the man that is made willing to have it muſt come where it is, as he is bidden <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.7. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1. <hi>come to the Waters, Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 13.1. —<hi>There ſhall be a fountain opened. —for ſin and for uneleanneſs.</hi> He that wants it, is to come to it, and not to ſend ſome body for it, as if it were not worth his going to; nor can any man take it out of it's place, or carry it to him to ſell; but he himſelf muſt come and buy it, where it runs in it's native Streams, <hi>from the Throne of God and of the Lamb;</hi> that is Chriſt, and he ſaith to the ſinner, <hi>Come unto me:</hi> And ſo in like manner, the Elemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Water in Gods Ordinance is to be come to.</p>
            <p>Tho <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> was not willing to go to the Waters (the Type of the Lord Jeſus for cleanſing, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 65 9.) as he was bidden; yet if he had not, the Water had never anſwered the end. <hi>John</hi> 5.7. Gods people are or ſhould be a willing people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John preached</hi> in all the Country about the Water, and Jeſus went from <hi>Galilee</hi> many miles to the water, and the Eunuch went out of his Chariot to the water, and <hi>Paul</hi> aroſe to the water. And thus, tho God hath an Ocean of Grace, and that this grace is free as a River, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 78.20, <hi>Iude</hi> 3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33 21. yet ſaith Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>They ſhall come weeping and mourning Iſa</hi> 48.18. And ſo tho his Ordinance of water be free, yet his people ſhall come to that, and not a little of that brought to Sprinkle, as if they were af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aid of too much, and as if too much wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.8. would ſignify too much grace, or us if, could they but have grace or ſanctity e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to carry them to Heaven, they would not have a drop more.</p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:99244:39"/>
            <p> Now Believer, if it come to paſs (by thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or any other means) that thou art wrought to a ſolid deſire publickly to profeſs thy ſelf Religious (<hi>Mar.</hi> 10.32. <hi>A believer on the Son of God for Salvation,</hi>) by an obediential ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to this Goſpelly ſettled Ordinance of believers baptiſm, and yet thou findeſt in thy ſelf frailty and inability to live a perfect <hi>holy Life,</hi> as becometh ſuch a profeſſor, and therefore thinkeſt with thy ſelf to delay <hi>baptiſm</hi> till thou art ſtronger fortified againſt Corruption, and better qualified for baptiſm: If ſo, then reſt on thy Lord Jeſus, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.26. and <hi>conclude to live thro the g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace of God, as well as thou ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, if not ſo well as thou wouldeſt;</hi> &amp; ſo reſolve to be baptized.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If thou believ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt with all thy heart, thou may'ſt be baptiſed.</hi> Believing or Faith is an heart quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying grace, and doth, and will bring forth the good fruits of an holy converſation, tho much of corrupt Nature ſtill remaineth. Then what hinders thy obedience to thy Saviours appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed believers baptiſm?</p>
            <p>Obſerve, That the Jaylor, <hi>Acts.</hi> 16. falling out of love with his ſins, ſpeak like a man of ſenſe and reaſon, <hi>What ſhall I do to be ſaved?</hi> And then the Apoſtle directs him high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er than ſenſe or reaſon, even to act as a man of Faith too; <hi>If thou wilt do,</hi> then, believe, <hi>do</hi> that without ſtaying for thy own Acts of Rigteouſneſs, <hi>believe on the Lord Jeſus Chriſt and thou ſhalt be ſaved.</hi> Do that firſt, and then thou art right to do more. Faith is the Root of other Sanctified Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, and alſo gives right to baptiſm.
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:99244:40"/>
               <hi>If thou believeſt, is the point that the Goſpel ſtands upon;</hi> art thou poor, art thou vile, nay, art thou the vileſt of ſinners, if thou believeſt, art changed, there's no Objection againſt thee: <hi>There's no Qualification like believing in the Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ified Ieſus of</hi> Nazareth, <hi>that hath undertaken to Sanctifie Sinners.</hi> Godly Parents and all the Forms of Worſhip, are not to be compared to believing with all the heart. Thus <hi>If thou believeſt with all thy heart thou mayeſt be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, Acts</hi> 8 37.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Art thou a Gentile Perſon?</hi> Then behold the Noble <hi>Ethopian</hi> Miniſter of State, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. riding in his Chariot with his Courtly Attendence, commanding all to ſtand ſtill while he g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es down into the Water with <hi>Philip,</hi> to be obedient to his Saviours diſpiſed Rule of dip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, (whereby he ſets himſelf againſt a Kingdom <hi>Ethiopia</hi>) and then he went on his way rejoycing at the greatneſs of his Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, according to <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.29. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Again,</hi> But it may be, thou haſt been a Perſecutor; That indeed is a dreadful thing, thou haſt hereby made War upon God and his Son Jeſus <hi>(that ſhould be thy Saviour)</hi> and all the Saints; and if thou mighteſt had thy Will, thou wouldeſt have done ſtrange things: But yet ſee the kindneſs of the Lord Jeſus to <hi>Saul,</hi> And when <hi>Sauls</hi> Convictions made him cry out, <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> He was then taught and ſent to <hi>Ananias,</hi> who ſaid to him, <hi>Why tarriest thou, ariſe and be baptized, Acts</hi> 22.16. And now to turn the ſtream of his Labours, the Lord Jeſus will have <hi>Saul</hi> become <hi>Paul,</hi> the Preacher of the everlaſting Goſpel, and a ſufferer for it too.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:99244:40"/>Hear what the Evangelical Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith of the fullneſs and freeneſs of the grace of the Goſpel to the poor and vile ſinner, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2. <hi>Ho, every one that thirsteth, come ye to the Waters</hi> (the grace of the Goſpel) <hi>&amp; he that hath no money, come ye &amp; buy, and eat; yea come buy Wine &amp; Milk without Money &amp; without price.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore do you ſpend your Money</hi> (your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires) <hi>for that which is not Bread, and your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for that which ſatisfies not.</hi> —</p>
            <p>The Son of God confirmeth this, <hi>John</hi> 7.37, 38.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the last day, that great day of the Feast, Jeſus ſtood, and cryed, ſaying, if any man thirſt, let him come unto me and drink.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that believeth on me, as the Scripture hath ſaid, out of his belly ſhall flow Rivers of living Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> (the Spirit and Grace of the Goſpel.)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And again,</hi> This exalted Saviour winds up his <hi>New Teſtament</hi> diſcovery of his Grace by his Proclamation in <hi>Revelations,</hi> 22.17. <hi>And the Spirit and the Bride ſay, Come, and let him that heareth ſay, Come; and let him that is a thirſt, Come; and whoſoever will let him take the Water of life freely.</hi> What wouldſt have more!</p>
            <p>O Sinner! that ſeeſt thy pollutions and art under the ſenſe of their deſerts; <hi>tho thou canst not by thy beſt Obedience anſwer the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of a holy ſevere Law,</hi> yet thou canſt by <hi>believing with all thy heart,</hi> anſwer the call of a holy reconciling Goſpel that freely of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers Chriſt for thy acceptance, and injoyns <hi>Believers Baptiſm</hi> as a tryal of thy ſaith: And ſo, <hi>if thou believeſt in (the ſufficiency of) the Lord Jeſus with all thy heart, thou mayst be baptiſed,</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:99244:41"/>
            <head>An Appendix.</head>
            <head type="sub">If any be offended at this Treatiſe, Then of them I Query.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 1. HOW comes it to paſs, that Liberty of Conſcience is not a Chriſtian's Priviledge now; As much as it was when the Men of your perſwaſion hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contended for it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 2. Are you an Infallible Judge of a Chriſtian's <hi>Reaſon Why</hi> he believes and obeys Gods Will, (in Scripture) <hi>Tho never any Papiſt or Protestant, could find a Iudge ſo ſafe for Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation as the Scripture.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 3. Is it not ſafeſt for a Chriſtian in the Conduct of his Life, to Follow the Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary Practice of Chriſt and his Apoſtles?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 4. Wherein do Perſons by sprinkling Infants, follow the Practice of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 5. The Apoſtles by Dipping Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers only, did faithfully diſcharge the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmal part of their Commiſſion. Then I Query, by what or whoſe commiſſion, are Infants now Sprinkled, for I never heard of another commiſſion by Divine Authority?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 6. Infants being Sprinkled without Chriſt's commiſſion for it: How doth it appear that Infants Sprinkling, will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by Chriſt, inſtead of believers baptiſm?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 7. Do not the Judgments on a Nation, often come for want of Reformation from Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, and the Image of it, in the Churches?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 8. Am not I in obeying and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending <hi>Forty</hi> New Teſtament Texts, more
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:99244:41"/>excuſable than ſome others, that with <hi>Non-ſequitors,</hi> Crown the many more Learned, that have pretended to defend Infant Sprinkling?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 9. Is it not ſafeſt for the finding of a New Teſtament Truth (<hi>Baptiſm)</hi> to compare all the New Teſtament Texts together, that mention that Truth, <hi>there being many whereby one Text may expound another?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 10. Why ſhould Infant Sprinklers by their Practice, occaſion <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con</hi> about Baptiſm? <hi>When one Text of forty about bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm will clearly prove that Goſpel baptiſm is not Infant Sprinkling, but believers Dipping?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 11. If Infants may be admitted Church Members, becauſe 'tis believed ſome of them are in the covenant to be in future time effectually called by the Goſpel to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. Then may not any ungodly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons be alſo admitted Church Members, becauſe ſome of them alſo are alike in the ſame Covenant to be in future time effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally called and ſaved?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 12. How can or doth Infants Sprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling anſwer Chriſt's deſign of Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, for dividing between the Church and the World? <hi>When experience and Scripture ſhews that the Infant Sprinkled Nations are groſly more World than Church,</hi> even Strangers and Enemies to Regeneration, tho all ſprinkled Church-Members.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 13. Why ſhould a Chriſtian be blamed for obeying and defending forty New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Text of Scripture for Believers Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm? <hi>When all the Men that ever oppoſed it, never ſhewed one Text that maketh any appearance for Infant Sprinkling.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:99244:42"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Query</hi> 14. Who is moſt juſtinable, he that ſhews his Obedience by many clear Texts of Scripture, or he that ſheweth his Practice by only ſallacious Conſequence and Preſumptions?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 15. Will not a Chriſtian do well to ſtand to the Doctrine of forty New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament Texts, tho' he be ſhot thro' and thro' with Ridiculous Speeches <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 16. Why ſhould I be too much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of my weakneſs, ſeeing my Caſe is true, and Truth is ſtrongeſt; and like much Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hath always tendency to clear it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 17. Whether is it beſt to obey God as Revealed in his Word, or obey Man as they Invent and Inſult?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 18. If Parents Imagine that they may make their Infants Church Members by their Sprinkling them, becauſe it is no where expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly forbidden, Then may they not do it by crouding any thing into the Worſhip of God that is not forbidden, or by giving their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſome other odd thing, <hi>That will be no abuſe to Baptiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 19. Tho' ſome groundleſsly may be offended at this Treatiſe, and catch at a word, is it not the Offendeds Duty to act like a Chriſtian, by conſidering the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of what is ſaid, rather than Sophiſter like, catch at a word, to ſophiſticate the truth, ſeeing every days experience ſhews, that <hi>The greatest Clarks and Counſels have tript in a Word, or Critricks have made them ſeem ſo to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Query</hi> 20. Why ſhould a Chriſtian take Infant Sprinkling for God's Ordinance, when never any Man proved, that God ordain'd it?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb n="81" facs="tcp:99244:42"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Chriſt and his Apoſt. preach believers baptiſm <hi>p. 1.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A new Creature hath aptneſs to Obedience <hi>p. 3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The four ſorts of People that don't like it <hi>p. 4.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Some Lovers of Chriſt dares be baptized. <hi>p. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Chriſtian Sprinklers left to their way = <hi>p. 5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm is after Faith and Repentance <hi>p. 7.8, 10, 19, 20, 24, 37, 41, 47. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptizing is Dipping, not Sprinkling. <hi>p. 7.12, 13, 17, 20, 24, 27, 35, 37. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptizing in much water. — <hi>p. 28, 36, 37.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infants are not Church Members. — <hi>p. 8, 47.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infants not baptiſed. — <hi>p. 29, 31, 33 47, 48.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Neither Believers Infants nor others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſprinkled <hi>p. 9.18, 21, 22, 29, 30, 31, 32. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An awakened ſoul ſees no right by nature <hi>p 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Repentance and baptiſm prepares for profeſſion <hi>p. 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Jeſus was dipt, and is our Example <hi>p. 11, 17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Jeſus choſe, and went miles to much water <hi>p. 11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Jeſus had not Water brought to him. — <hi>p. 12.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>God approved obedience in much Water, <hi>p. 12, 24.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Tho ſome reject, yet others rece. bapt. <hi>p. 13, 15, 18.25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Commiſſion is to teach and baptiſe <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infant ſprink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. makes all world &amp; no Church <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Christ's preſence promiſed to preaching &amp; bap. <hi>p. 14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How dare ſome Miniſters ſay, <hi>In the Name. p. 15.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Election directeth not to Infant Sprink. <hi>p. 16, 22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>God ſanctifieth, &amp; Man baptiſeth — <hi>p. 16.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>God accepts only what he hath appointed. <hi>p. 18.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believing and baptiſm are joyned together <hi>p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sprinkling furthers not Infants Salvation. <hi>p. 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Never any believer hurt in baptiſing. <hi>p 19.</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:99244:43"/>
               <item>Believers baptm. hath a Commſn. but Inſn. none <hi>p. 19</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Naaman</hi> adviſed to obey Gods Will — <hi>p. 20</hi>
               </item>
               <item>An <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nbelievers Child's baptiſm is null <hi>p. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Not Election but Believing give right to bapt. <hi>p. 22</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Duty excludes Infants from Baptiſm <hi>p. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Learned own that baptize is dip. <hi>p. 26</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſed at <hi>Enou,</hi> becauſe of much water <hi>p. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>None but Diſciples were baptiſed — <hi>p 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infant Sprinkling a Counterfeit <hi>to,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>p. 29.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm is Commanded. <hi>p. 30, 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>They that gladly received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he word baptiſed. <hi>p. 31</hi>
               </item>
               <item>As one, ſo another is ſaved by grace <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Not Covenant but Regen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> gives right to bap. <hi>p. 32</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Men and Women, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o Infants baptiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <hi>p. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>H.</hi> Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>id m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch to little purpoſe. <hi>p. 33</hi>
               </item>
               <item>'Tis foolery to d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aptiſm was Dipping <hi>p. 35</hi>
               </item>
               <item>'Tis affronting to change Gods Ordinance <hi>p. 35, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm follows the ſign of a change — <hi>p. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſed with the Spirit, fits for Water <hi>p. 37</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lydia</hi> had neither husband nor children <hi>p 38 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Jaylor had no Infants — — <hi>p. 40</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believers baptiſm is no Rebaptiſm — <hi>p. 42</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a ſign of waſhing from ſin <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Much water is an Emblem of Grace <hi>p. 43</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm a ſign of death, burial &amp; Reſurrect. <hi>p. 44, 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paul</hi> did baptiſe ſeveral — — <hi>p. 45</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſed in the Cloud and Sea — <hi>p. 46</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſed into one body — <hi>p. 47</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſed for the dead, excludes Infants <hi>p. 48</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Not Infants but believers put on Christ <hi>p. 49</hi>
               </item>
               <item>There's but one baptiſm, thats dipping believers <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believers baptiſm figureth <hi>4</hi> things — <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sprinkling is a profanation of baptiſm <hi>p. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dipping ſhews Christs Death and Refurrect. <hi>p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:99244:43"/>
               <item>Several Metephors explain baptiſm = <hi>p. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm is a foundation Doctrine — <hi>p. 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Church robb'd of her Names, <hi>&amp;c. p, 52</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Noahs</hi> Flood a Figure of baptiſm — <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Baptiſm is a ſign of ſanctification — <hi>p. 53</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Perſons, and Mode of Baptiſing <hi>p. 54.55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>How Infant ſprinkling came in faſhion <hi>p. 56</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Nine Evil Tendencies of Infant Sprinkling <hi>p. 57</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Objections Anſwered = <hi>p. 58, 59, 60.61.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Difference between ſprinkling &amp; baptiſing <hi>p. 62, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Infant ſprinklers makes ſelf-contradiction <hi>p. 67</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A ſight of a believer at baptiſing. <hi>p. 68</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of Reproaches and Sufferings <hi>p. 69</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The dignity of the Lord Jeſus — <hi>p. 70</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Likeneſs between grace and much wat. <hi>p. 71,</hi> to, <hi>74</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Humaene Frailty hindereth not baptiſm <hi>p. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believing is qualification for baptiſm <hi>p. 75</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Gentility hindereth not baptiſm <hi>p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Perſecutor called and baptiſed — <hi>p. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Proclamation for all to come <hi>p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Believers admitted in a way of Faith <hi>p. 77</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Twenty Quereis for Baptiſm = <hi>p. 78, 79 80</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>p. 5. l. 1. ſ. the ſinner r. <hi>this ſinner</hi> p. 16. l. 33. f. ſc p. 27. r. <hi>ſe</hi> p. 26. p. 27. l. 31. r. counted. p. 33. l. 34 r. of hardneſs. p. 36. l. 1. r. <hi>Acts</hi> 9.17.18. p. 36 l. 4. f. if it had r. <hi>it had</hi> p. 51 l. 29 f. up r. <hi>upon</hi> l. 30 f. they r. <hi>ſo they</hi> f. up r. <hi>upon</hi> p. 62 l. 29 f. which r. <hi>after which.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>Advertſement.</head>
            <p>At <hi>London</hi> are many larger Treatiſes of <hi>Believers Baptiſm,</hi> which I ſhall willingly help the inquiſitive to, or to theſe.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
